<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two sermons the former deliuered at Pauls Crosse the foure and twentieth of March, 1615. being the anniuersarie commemoration of the Kings most happie succession in the Crowne of England. The latter at the Spittle on Monday in Easter weeke, 1613. By Iohn VVhite D.D.</title>
            <author>White, John, 1570-1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1048:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two sermons the former deliuered at Pauls Crosse the foure and twentieth of March, 1615. being the anniuersarie commemoration of the Kings most happie succession in the Crowne of England. The latter at the Spittle on Monday in Easter weeke, 1613. By Iohn VVhite D.D.</title>
                  <author>White, John, 1570-1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 85, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Field for William Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20569:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20569:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Two Sermons;</hi> THE FORMER DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVERED AT PAVLS CROSSE THE FOVRE AND TWEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of March, 1615. being the anniuerſarie commemoration of the Kings moſt happie ſucceſſion in the Crowne of England. <hi>THE LATTER AT THE Spittle on Monday in Eaſter weeke,</hi> 1613. By IOHN VVHITE D.D.</p>
            <q>
               <p>My Sonne, feare thou God and the King, and meddle not with them that are giuen to change.</p>
               <bibl>Prou. <hi>24.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Richard Field, featuring an anchor suspended by a hand from the clouds (McKerrow 192)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Richard Field for William Barret. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20569:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20569:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VERTVOVS AND NOBLE LA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, the Ladie Crofts, wife to my worthie Patron, Sir Iohn Crofts of Saxham: all comfort in the mercies and grace of God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Madam, I ſend you what I preached, not long ſince, in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne and deuout audience, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeciall occaſion. For ſuch is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the curioſitie or religion of Hearers, that ſometime they will haue vs preach in print. He that could do it well, in one ſenſe, were a man fit for this age; though in my ſenſe, it is fitter for many then for my ſelfe: who knowing mine owne imperfections, and the different operation of a mouing voyce and breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe letters, am therfore naturally timorous of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cenſures; and had kept my lines within doores if either importunitie had not inticed them abroad, or I had not feared their ſtealing out at a back dore. Now, as they are, I commend them to your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb facs="tcp:20569:3"/>it hauing bene, time out of mind, a courteſie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Preſſe, to take vp the Paſſe where it beſt affects. When I liued farre remote, Sir Iohn Crofts, your husband, my worthie and louing Patrone, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing neuer ſeene me, ſent and called me to the place I haue: ſince which time it hath pleaſed both <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>you ſelfe,</hi> and your <hi>Noble children,</hi> and my <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable LADIE CHEANY</hi> (with whom you liued in the ſtraiteſt band of loue vntill God, by a bleſſed death, in her ripe age, tooke her to his mercie) ſo much to fauour me, that thereby I haue bene the better both encouraged and enabled to my ſtudies, which were falling to the ground for want of means. And if that were not, yet what I haue ſeene ſince, in the courſe of your life, and the order of your family, were enough to binde all good minds, that honour Vertue, vnto you; whoſe zeale to <hi>Religion,</hi> and loue to <hi>Learning,</hi> and continuall <hi>exerciſe</hi> therein both by <hi>reading</hi> and <hi>practiſe,</hi> ioyned with ſuch promptnes of <hi>memorie</hi> and <hi>modeſtie</hi> in ſpeaking, giues you intereſt in all either Learned, or Godly, &amp; makes you worthy of more then my poore words can attribute. Saint Ierome commends a Ladie becauſe ſhe made her daughters and gentlewomen that were about her <hi>daily to reade and learne ſomewhat out of the Scripture:</hi> a kind of commendation now
<pb facs="tcp:20569:3"/>worne out of faſhion, like a ſute of apparell of the old make: yet your Ladiſhip hath not refuſed it; that he who hath ſeene your children and attendants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you, priuate, at worke, hath doubted which were the worke; the Reading of ſome, while others were working, or the working of others while ſome were reading. Which parts men obſeruing in perſons of your ranke, haue taken libertie, without all feare, and freely, to ſpeake thereof; and the wiſeſt that haue bene, ſuch as Ignatius, Chryſoſtome, Ierome, Baſil, Nazianzen, Saint Paul himſelfe and the holy Euangeliſts, haue mentioned them; and more then mentioned them; left vs thoſe memorials of them that the Church of God could not haue ſpared: as may be ſeene by their affectionate writing of, and to, the <hi>Maries, Lydia, Lois, Eunice, Caſſobolites, Olympias, Laeta, Demetrias, Paula, Euſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium, Celantia, Saluina,</hi> and diuers more; whoſe vertues therein mentioned are a great part of that which hath taught and giuen example to noble wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in all ages ſince. For <hi>coniugal loue, mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pietie, matronly grauitie, wiſedome, boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, humilitie, hoſpitalitie, vertue,</hi> ſhall be both regiſtred, and commended, and imitated, and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, when the contrarie ſhall be contemned in the greateſt, and, now and then, ſent downe to the graue
<pb facs="tcp:20569:4"/>with a peale of ſatyres. Go forward then and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine what God hath giuen you; and as theſe things are yours in an eminent manner, ſo hold them faſt, and value them aboue your husbands ſtate, or your patronage: much more aboue glittering apparell and worldly pleaſures, and thoſe vanities and exceſſes where with ſo manie pleaſe themſelues and no bodie elſe. And as here they yeeld you honor and reſpect, ſo in Death (which determines all our actions, and layes the pleaſures of ſinne vpon Gods cold earth) you ſhall taſte the benefite thereof: for the delights of the fleſh, and the pride of life, will poiſon the graue; but the feare of God ſhall be recompenced with <hi>Honor,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Eternall life:</hi> which things are daily behight vnto you, your godly husband, and vertuous children, in his praiers to God,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By him that is at your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhips ſeruice</hi> IO. WHITE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20569:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT PAVLES CROSSE vpon the foure and twentieth of March, 1615. being the anniuerſarie commemoration of the Kings moſt happie ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Crowne of England.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. TIM. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I exhort therefore, that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayer, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, and giuing of thankes, be made for all men: for Kings, and for all that are in authoritie: that we may leade a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe, and honeſtie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND is it true, that all theſe things are ſo indeed as they ſeeme vnto vs? are we not deceiued? do we certainly ſee one another indeed, that we dreame not of that which is but a fancie and beguiles vs? are we out of our beds, waking, and mouing, and truly vnderſtanding what befalles vs? is it day-light? are our eyes open? is not ſleepe ſtill vpon vs, or waking dreames, preſenting vs with imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? are they not ſhadowes that are about vs? Is it credible that a ſinfull Nation, ſo ill deſeruing at the hands of God; ſo watcht by enemies in our boſome, the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20569:5"/>moſt cruell and mercileſſe that euer were; and threatned by him and his that thinke they haue power to ſhut vp heauen, and reſtraine the influence of euery creature; that waited for nothing, as this day, but confuſion and euery miſchiefe to fall vpon vs that their wrath could procure: is it, I ſay, poſſible that a people in ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſhipwracke, in good-earneſt without dreaming, ſhould, notwithſtanding, liue and breathe the ſame life we did, enioy the ſame mercies of our God, the ſame ſecurity, the ſame peace, both of State and Church; and they lie at our feete like the fiue Kings of Canaan,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 10.24.</note> that meant to haue deuoured vs? and this day, which they propheſied ſhould haue bene the diſmalleſt that euer roſe vpon the kingdome, aſſemble alſo together in ioy and triumph, men, women and little children, to celebrate our peace, ringing and ſinging, and reioycing before the Lord our maker?</p>
            <p>Parſons, the Ieſuite, a man well knowne to our State, and by his owne, thought a great Stateſman himſelfe, and wiſe (but he was <hi>a cab of dung,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Reg. 6.25.</note> an <hi>Aſſes head ſold</hi> to the Pope <hi>for</hi> 80. <hi>ſiluerlings,</hi> and his friends roſe vp in a miſty morning when a ſheepe ſeemed to them as big as an oxe) in the late Queenes dayes, publiſht in print, that<note n="*" place="margin">Anſwer to the libel of Engl iuſt. pag. <hi>176. &amp; 185.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>By the vncertainty of the next heire, our Countrey was in the most dreadfull and deſperate caſe, in the greateſt miſerie and moſt dangerous termes, that euer it was ſince or before the Conquest: and in farre worſe then any Countrey of Chriſtendome; by the certainty of moſt bloudy, ciuill, and forrein warres: all our wealth and felicitie whatſoeuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending vpon a few vncertaine dayes of Queene Elizabeths life;</hi> and ſuch as hoped otherwiſe he calles, <hi>common per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>thriftleſſe yonkers.</hi> And this was the generall cry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20569:5"/>and expectation of them all: that what we now ſee to the contrarie, through Gods infinite mercie, againſt their conſpiracies, may ſeeme a dreame; and our mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this day, to celebrate this mercie, may ſeeme a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or deluſion of our ſenſes. And indeed for men to be thus miſtaken in their ſleepe it is ordinarie. For, <hi>Eſay</hi> 29. 8. <hi>A hungry man dreames, and behold he eateth; a thirſtie man dreames, and lo he is drinking: and yet when they wake their ſoule is empty.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> For ſuch is the nature of dreaming: (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>it is full of deceit, and will ſet vs a playing with monſters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 But that which we are about is neither dreame nor deluſion, nor are you aſleepe, but waking, and you really enioy vnder your hands all that you thinke on; and ſee a wonder beyond any euer dreamt of: and it is day, euen cleare day-light, one of the lightſomeſt that euer ſhined on our nation; the Sunne is vp, and hath ſhewed vs the vnſpeakeable mercies of our God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.24.</note> 
               <hi>This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will reioyce and be glad therein.</hi> And long may this day endure; like the day of Ioſuah when <hi>the Sunne ſtood ſtill in Gibeon, and the Moone in the valley of Aialon:</hi> Let the tender mercies of God euermore enlighten it with the day-ſpring from aboue: let eternitie embrace it and claſpe it round about, that it may be ioyned with the daies of heauen, and meaſured together with eternitie: let clouds nor miſts, nor ſtormes, nor tempeſt, nor the <hi>ſmoke of the bottomleſſe pit,</hi> euer ouerſhadow it; nor the darke night tread vpon it: let it ſhew the paths of righteouſneſſe, and the wayes of God to all people: in the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of let vs ſee long peace, and the continuance of true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the amendment of our liues, and the downefall
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20569:6"/>of Antichriſt. Write this day, as<note n="a" place="margin">Ep. ad Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ.</note> Ignatius ſaith of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day; <hi>the Lady and miſtris of all other dayes:</hi> the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed day which the Lord hath made, therein to ſhew the riches of his mercies to the vnworthieſt nation that euer was; God grant we may be able to reioyce<note n="b" place="margin">Tertul. apol.</note> 
               <hi>Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia non laſciuia: not laſciuiouſly but righteouſly;</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Euthym. in Pſal. 117.</note> 
               <hi>vt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brem Deo ac ſplendidam ſolemnitatem agamus: that we may make our ſolemnity ſuch as the goodneſſe and greatneſſe of God requireth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 To which purpoſe the words of my text do ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtruct vs. They are an admonition touching the matter of prayer, wherein the Apoſtle requires that, without limitation, we <hi>pray</hi> and <hi>giue thankes for all men:</hi> but namely for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>publike Magiſtrates,</hi> and ſuch as are <hi>eminent in the State,</hi> that the Goſpell may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated, peace, vertue and iuſtice, may be maintained. For, <hi>Prou.</hi> 29. <hi>When good men are in authoritie, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall reioyce; but when the wicked beare rule, the land mournes:</hi> And <hi>Eſay</hi> 49. <hi>Kings ſhall be thy nouriſhers, and Queenes thy nurſes;</hi> when God will put his Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of the Magiſtrate as it were to nurſe, let <hi>thankes</hi> be rendred to him for his ordinance, and <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> and <hi>prayers,</hi> and <hi>interceſſion,</hi> be made for their continuance in well doing; that the State vnder them may be in <hi>peace,</hi> and be gouerned <hi>iuſtly</hi> and <hi>religiouſlie.</hi> He complaines immediatly before, of ſome that, lately by their apoſtacie from their religion, had hindred the Goſpell, and in dammaged the Church: had there bene a Chriſtian zealous Emperour, a Conſtantine, a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius, a Iouinian, a Iohn Fredericke, this either had not fallen out, or had not done ſo much hurt; now, in this want, all that could be done was to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20569:6"/>which being too little for the remouing of ſo great a miſchiefe, he <hi>exhorts</hi> and <hi>requires,</hi> that <hi>principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie aboue all things</hi> a care be had in the Church, that <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>thankſgiuing</hi> be made for <hi>all men,</hi> that no man fall from <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>a good conſcience:</hi> and namely for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> that ſuch as fall being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the ſecular power, the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>quietneſſe,</hi> the <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>honeſtie,</hi> of Church and State may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. This is the ſenſe and connexion of the text.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Wherein our Apoſtle affirmes three things. Firſt, the exerciſe that he would haue vſed. Secondly, the matter of this exerciſe. Thirdly, the end why we ſhould thus exerciſe. The exerciſe is <hi>prayer.</hi> The matter of this prayer, for <hi>all men,</hi> and namely for <hi>Kings and Magiſtrates.</hi> The end why, <hi>that we may leade a quiet and calme life, in godlineſſe and honeſtie.</hi> In handling where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you will ſoone perceiue me to omit many points that are incident: but I muſt attend vpon the time, and will aime onely at the occaſion.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Firſt, the exerciſe commended is <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>thankſgiuing.</hi> For, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. <hi>the weapons of our war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare are not carnall, but mightie:</hi> where Saint Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome notes vpon that place, <hi>not our wealth, or power, or flattering of our ſelues can ſaue vs, but the power of God.</hi> This duty is expreſſed in foure termes: <hi>ſupplication, prayer, interceſſion, thankſgiuing.</hi> The ſtreame of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and expoſitors, old and new, commonly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh theſe as foure ſeuerall kindes of prayer, albeit they ſcarce agree in defining the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The moſt receiued diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is, that <hi>ſupplications</hi> are for the pardon of our ſins. <hi>Prayers,</hi> the vow and promiſe, that we make to God, touching the amendment of our life. <hi>Interceſſion</hi> when
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20569:7"/>we pray for others. <hi>Thankſgiuing,</hi> when we praiſe his Name, for the graces he beſtowes vpon vs. Others, who ſeeme to come nearer the point, expound them thus: when we pray God to turne away euill, this is <hi>ſupplication:</hi> when to giue vs the good we need, this is <hi>prayer:</hi> when we ſimply craue any thing whatſoeuer, this is <hi>interceſſion:</hi> when we bleſſe God for his mercies, this is <hi>thankſgiuing.</hi> For my owne part, I thinke it more probable and eaſier to defend, that the Apoſtle intends no ſuch diuiſion, in regard of the matter of Prayer; but onely to commend the ſame thing in diuerſe words, according to the cuſtome of the Scripture; for howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>thankſgiuing</hi> may be diſtinguiſhed; yet the reſt either cannot, by reaſon they do all of them eſſentially include each other; or are not, in this place, by reaſon the definitions aſſigned will not ſo aptly ſute with the Text. I will therefore follow<note n="*" place="margin">In Pſal. 140.</note> Hilary, who applies them to the ſeuerall <hi>motions of the minde</hi> wherewith we ought to pray: for in all prayer it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the mind be lift vp to God by charitie, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, and faith: our <hi>charitie</hi> deſires the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as well as our owne; our <hi>humilitie</hi> prayes with all ſubmiſſion to God, and acknowledges what we receiue of his mercie: our <hi>faith</hi> makes vs flie to God alone, and in his goodneſſe to repoſe our confidence. According to which expoſition, this diſtinction of words is not founded on the matter of prayer, ſo much as on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall <hi>habits</hi> and <hi>motions</hi> of the mind whence true prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er proceedeth, and wherewith it is informed. For eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moral action is ſpecified by the intention of the doer: &amp; therefore the intentions or motions of the mind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diuers, the ſame prayer hath alſo diuers appellations.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20569:7"/>
            <p n="6">6 Which things thus expounded, we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what the thing is that is, moſt effectuall and auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable to the proſperitie of a kingdome, that Kings and Rulers may ſucceed and hold out, to the comfort and happineſſe of their people, our Apoſtle bidding make <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>ſupplication,</hi> and <hi>giue thankes</hi> for theſe things. Not that policie, or ſtrength, and counſell may be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, for that were tempting of God, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the meanes which he hath appointed; but becauſe it is God alone that giues motion to theſe things, and the influxe of his prouidence makes them effectuall: <hi>By him Kings reigne, and Princes rule, and all the Nobles and Iudges of the earth,</hi> ſaith Solomon, <hi>Prou.</hi> 8. and <hi>Iob</hi> 12. <hi>He leades Counſellers away ſpoiled, and makes the Iudges fooles: he looſeth the collar of Kings, and guirdeth their loines with a girdle: he powreth contempt vpon Princes, and weakeneth the ſtrength of the mightie.</hi> If his helpe and mercie be wanting, the ſinewes of a State will ſhrinke, and the wiſedome of the wiſe will be infatua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; policy wil be no better then lunacy, glory will turne into miſerie, and armies of men will but helpe to make the fal heauier.<note place="margin">Pachymer.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>For what God will haue come to paſſe will outworke all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane conſideration;</hi> and then, as Nazianzen ſpeaketh, <hi>Tandem ſubmergetur nauis quae multos ad portum foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appulit: hope which vſeth to bring the moſt miſerable to the ſhore, it ſelfe ſhall ſinke and periſh.</hi> Thus the mightieſt States haue bene diſſolued, and all worldly power, when God abandons it, falles to the ground. That, as Sidonius ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. ep. 7.</note> the moſt potent and politicke man that liues, may lie, <hi>veluti vomitu Fortunae nauſeautis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putus:</hi> as if Fortune from her loathing ſtomacke had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20569:8"/>vomited him vp, and ſpit him vpon the ground: to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent which danger, and to ſaue from enemies, the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and religion of the ſubiect haue alwaies bene the beſt meanes.<note n="a" place="margin">Exo. 17.</note> When Amalek fought againſt Iſrael, Moſes, by his prayer, aſſured the victorie.<note n="b" place="margin">2 Chro. 20.</note> When Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat was in danger, he prayed to God with his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>We know not what to do, but our eyes are vpon thee.</hi> And this remedy hath neuer failed the people that haue vſed it. Saint Ambroſe<note n="c" place="margin">De obit. Theod.</note> reports of Theodoſius, that in a fought field againſt the tyrant Eugenius, when he had almoſt loſt the day, alighting from his horſe, and ſtepping before his armie, in the face of the enemie, he onely kneeled downe and cried to God, <hi>Vbi eſt Deus Theodoſij,</hi> Where is Theodoſius his God? and wonne the day.<note n="d" place="margin">Iuſt. apol. 2.</note> When Marcus Aurelius, in the field againſt 970000. enemies, was in diſtreſſe for want of water, the prayers of the Chriſtians relieued him: <hi>cum ipſa ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione affuit Deus,</hi> ſaith Iuſtin Martyr, ſo ſoone as they had prayed God was with them; and he receiued the praiers of the Church as a garriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into his Empire. The Macabees had their name of this, that in their colours, when they went into the field, they had fiue letters, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, euery better ſignifying a word, <hi>Mi cha Elohim be Iiſrael: Who is like to God in Iſrael:</hi> all their confidence was in God, on whom they called &amp; depended. This is ſo well knowne and ratified by experience, that I neuer read of any State, Chriſtian or Gentile, but they haue acknowledged it. That not the Church alone, but infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels in their idolatrie, and heretickes in their ſchiſme, haue had recourſe thereto. What more ſolemne with the ancient Greekes, Romanes, Carthaginians, or the Turkes and Barbarian at this day, then to enioyne
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20569:8"/>prayer and religious ſeruice to their idols, for the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of their State? The onely errour among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, being, either the performing of this exerciſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cleanſing their life, or the forgetting or neglecting thereof, or the caſting it behind ſtrength and policy, which ought to follow it. Your Biſhops and Preachers honour and affect the outward policy of the State as much as nay in the kingdome do, and take as much comfort in the ſtrength of our nation, the wealth of the ſubiect, the vigilancie and circumſpection of the Counceller, the courage and skill of the martiall man, and will be as ſorie to ſee them decay: yet will we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſſe to crie in your eares,<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 33.17.</note> 
               <hi>A horſe is but a vaine thing to ſaue.</hi> The SPANISH ARMADA, and POW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER-TREASON, and ALL THE TREASONS that haue bene plotted beſide, haue taught vs, that not the policy or counſell, or ſtrength of our nation, but the mercie of God, the infinite, tender, ſauing mercie of our God, hearing the prayer of his people, was it that reſcued, when ſtrength lay aſleepe on Dalilahs knees, and policy was blind, and all humane wit foreſaw no danger: the which may teach vs for euer not to boaſt too loud of great Brittains ſtrength, but to remember PRAYER, and by maintaining RELIGION, and leading the ſubiect forward to DEVOTION, and by ſuppreſſing that which hath poiſoned the prayers of thouſands among vs, to procure that God euery where, by <hi>lifting vp pure hands,</hi> be called vpon, and bleſſed for his mercifull prouidence ouer the State.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And we muſt not onely be mindfull of the <hi>duty,</hi> but carefull alſo that we diſcharge it <hi>well;</hi> by reaſon that as true prayer rightly informed will preſerue, ſo that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20569:9"/>which is otherwiſe will do no good: therefore, as Saint Chryſoſtome ſaith: <hi>Not onely the flowers, whereof the garland is made, must be freſh and louely, but the hands alſo of him that makes the garland must be cleane.</hi> For Saint Iames<note n="f" place="margin">Iac. 4.3.</note> ſaith, <hi>You aske and receiue not, becauſe you aske not as you ſhould.</hi> We muſt ioyne three things with prayer, if we will be heard. Firſt, <hi>the hands lift vp must be pure,</hi> that we liue not in ſinne. <hi>Eſay,</hi> 1. <hi>When ye multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie your prayers I will not heare you, for your hands are full of bloud,</hi> in which caſe,<note n="g" place="margin">Vit. Moſ. lib 3.</note> ſaith Philo, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Sacrifice is abominable, ſeruice vnholy, and prayer ominous:</hi> For<note n="h" place="margin">Pro. 28.9.</note> 
               <hi>he that turnes his eare from hearing and obeying the word, euen his prayer ſhall be abominable.</hi> Next, we muſt <hi>perſeuere without wearineſſe,</hi> praying daily, and waiting patiently, if any thing be amiſſe, and daily giuing thankes; So the Scripture tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth:<note n="i" place="margin">Col. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Continue in prayer, and watch thereunto.</hi> For the State hath her daily charge, and daily enemies, and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dangers: as a ſhip by ſea in a long voyage; where perſeuerance, euery man in his charge, is it that makes a proſperous iourney. Thirdly, the <hi>mind must be lift vp to God by the puritie and the deuotion thereof:</hi> there muſt be <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>confidence,</hi> that God will heare vs; <hi>reuerence</hi> of his Name, <hi>meekenſſe</hi> of ſpirit, <hi>loue</hi> to one another; and, as our Apoſtle ſaith in the eight verſe: <hi>holy hands without wrath or doubting.</hi> And in the point of <hi>Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing,</hi> there muſt not onely be in the vnderſtanding an apprehenſion of the mercies of God receiued, but in the will ſuch a ſpirituall ioy therein, and loue to God therefore, that the mind thereby be reuoked from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing in any thing elſe, but onely in God that ſaues vs. This is the prayer that pierceth heauen: <hi>Praeteruolat
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20569:9"/>montes &amp; nubes, penetrat coelum, &amp; implet mundum, ecce quouſque volat vox clamantis animae: It flies higher then mountaines or the cloudes: it filleth the world and pierceth heauen, when the ſoule cries to God with an earnest voice.</hi> When Arius infeſted the Church, the ſaying was, that Athanaſius reſiſted him with his learning, but Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the deuout Biſhop vanquiſht him with his prayers. Socrates telleth that when a terrible fire in Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, faſtened on a great part of the citie, and tooke hold of the Church, the Biſhop thereof went to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and falling downe vpon his knees, would not riſe from thence till the fire, blaſing in the windowes, and flaſhing at euery dore to come in, was vanquiſht, &amp; the Church preſerued: with the flouds of his deuotion, he ſlaked the furie of the threatning element. The ſame ſhal be the force of our prayers for his Maieſtie and the State, if we be faithfull therein: hereſie may rage, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon conſpire, and enemies caſt fire-brands; but we will <hi>truſt in him that neuer forſaketh ſuch as cal vpon his name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 The next thing mentioned in the text, is the matter of our prayers, containing the <hi>Perſons</hi> &amp; the thing to be prayed for: touching the <hi>Perſons,</hi> he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioynes that we pray, firſt, generally, for <hi>all men:</hi> and then particularly, for <hi>Kings and all in authoritie.</hi> Firſt, for <hi>all men,</hi> the reaſon whereof is yeelded, verſe the fourth, becauſe <hi>God wills that all men be ſaued, and come to the knowledge of the truth:</hi> and <hi>Chriſt the Redeemer,</hi> in ſome true manner or other, <hi>gaue himſelfe a ranſome for all.</hi> Our deuotion muſt attend Gods will, that what he willes we pray for, that ſo his will may be done in earth as it is in heauen. There were no difficultie in this point if by, ALL MEN, no more were meant the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>All</hi> the elect,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20569:10"/>or <hi>All</hi> that profeſſe Chriſt, and are true members of the Church. For in theſe the mercie of God, and the effect of our prayers infallibly and apparantly ſhew themſelues: for, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Whom he predestinated, them he calles, and whom he calles thoſe he iustifies, and whom he iuſtifies them he alſo glorifies.</hi> But when we ſee with our eies innumerable companies, and whole nations, to be Barbarians, Infidels, Iewes, Idolaters, Heretickes, Atheiſts, Profane, Excommunicate, Enemies; and when we certainly know by the Scripture, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controuerſie beleeue, no ſmall part of mankind, in Gods decree and eternall purpoſe, to ſtand reprobate and reiected from ſaluation, and all the effects of electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, (whether in the maſſe of ſinne or not, and whether vpon the foreſight of their vnbeleefe or otherwiſe, all is one to the point of this difficultie:) when, I ſay, it is of all hands yeelded that there be ſo many reprobates, denied the grace of election, and from all eternitie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, or<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rom <hi>9.22.</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, made vp, finiſhed.</note> 
               <hi>finiſhed,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaketh, to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (for what God executes in time he willes in eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,) what ſhall we ſay to Prayer and Thankſgiuing for theſe? or what benefite can either they or we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thereby? Marke my anſwer. Touching the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer the caſe is not difficult, ſuch being the extent of the grace of God, that there is<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 10.34.</note> 
               <hi>no reſpect of perſon with him;</hi> but either Iew or Gentile, or Barbarian or Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian, or idolater or hereticke, may reape the benefite of our prayers, if it be no more but the outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this life; which God by his owne example,<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>making the Sunne to ſhine vpon the iuſt and vniuſt,</hi> will haue vs vow and wiſh them. And abſtracting from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, which is hid from vs, and conſidering no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20569:10"/>more in them but what we can infalliblie ſee, God can or may alſo giue the meanes, that they may be called to the truth and be ſaued. For ſo we ſee the riches of Gods mercie to extend it ſelfe to the ſinfulleſt and wofulleſt perſons that euer were. Gentiles in ſome ages haue bin conuerted; idolaters, Atheiſts, heretickes in all ages haue bene reclaimed and ioyned to the Church; and if they be not, yet we to whom God hath no imparted his ſecret purpoſes, ſee nothing in them but we may deſire it: Nay the more miſerie and infidelitie we ſee them drowned in, the more doth Chriſtian pietie bind vs to pitie their ſtate, &amp; deſire their conuerſion. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note n="m" place="margin">Liturg. Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob. &amp; alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> in the ancient Liturgies of the Church we often reade, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and haue mercy vpon <hi>All men:</hi> And Celeſtin, a godly Biſhop of the ancient Church:<note n="n" place="margin">Ep. ad epiſe. Gall.</note> 
               <hi>Apud diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam clementiam, ſanctarum ſedium praeſides humani gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aguntcauſam; vt legem credendi lex ſtatuat ſupplican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di: The Biſhops of the Church,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>commend to God the cauſe of all mankind, and</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Not that, as we pray for all men, ſo God will ſaue all men; but that as we pray for All, ſo we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue it to be his will we pray for all, and that God in all eſtates of men will ſaue whom he pleaſeth.</note> 
               <hi>by their prayers ſhew what we are to beleeue. They intreate God to giue Infidels faith, Idolaters truth, Iewes light, heretickes repentance, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes humilitie.</hi> But touching the reprobate there is more to be added. For albeit no man pray God to ſaue them whom he, in his ſecret counſell, knowes to be reprobate, that is to ſay, to change or abrogate his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall decree: yet foure things are certaine touching them, which I will lay downe in ſo many concluſions. Firſt, <hi>We pray not God to</hi> SAVE <hi>thoſe whom we beleeue he hath reprobated from all eternitie:</hi> the reaſon is, for no man prayes for that which God hath made no promiſe to grant, as there is no promiſe that he will ſaue him or
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20569:11"/>thoſe whom he hath reiected from election, but the contrarie; an expreſſe reuelation that he will condemne them. Secondly, <hi>it is vnknowne to all men who in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular are reprobate.</hi> For albeit a man may diſcerne vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſignes of reprobation in ſome, as in a Turke or a Iew; yet, ſpeaking precizely, the reprobation of this or that man is a ſecret laid vp in Gods owne boſome, and he that gueſſes at it may be deceiued, in as much as Gods works of grace are ſecret,<note n="o" place="margin">Ro. 11.23.</note> that he who to day is a wilde oliue, to morrow in an inſtant may be graffed in. Yea he that moſt ſtrongly thinkes himſelfe a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, as Spira of Padua did, may ſuddenly be preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the grace of God, and brought to his iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for any thing that we know. Thirdly, <hi>the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of prayer no where diſtinguiſheth betweene elect and reprobate, but generally binds to pray for all men.</hi> There is a diſtinction, and God that made it, knowes it; but we muſt do our owne worke, and let God alone with his. For, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. <hi>Secret things belong to the Lord thy God, but things which are reuealed, to vs, that we may do the words of the Law.</hi> And, to authorize vs to pray for any man, it is ſufficient that, all things conſidered, it is <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> poſſible he may be ſaued: which morall poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may be had, touching the ſaluation of any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, if God, by reuelation, or ſome other certaine way, ſhew not the contrarie. I call it <hi>morall</hi> poſſibilitie which, <hi>in our vnderſtanding,</hi> may be ſo, by reaſon there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things which, <hi>for any thing we know,</hi> may fall out to effect it, albeit abſolutely, in Gods knowledge, it ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be. <hi>Metaphyſicall poſſibilitie,</hi> hauing no ingredience into our morall actions, is not enough no giue this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: &amp; therfore how vehement ſoeuer the coniectures
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20569:11"/>&amp; likelihoods of any mans reprobation be, yet ſtill we haue fiue things that ouercome ſuch coniectures, and make the poſſibilitie of his ſaluation morall to vs. Firſt, the generall promiſes of the Goſpell offred to all. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the efficacy of Gods grace when it comes. Thirdly, the poſſibility that it may come. Fourthly, the commandement to pray that it may come. Fiftly, the examples of diuerſe in deſperate ſtate, to whom it hath come. All which being put together and well conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, make it morally poſſible that he may be called; and ouercome the moſt violent coniectures and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the contrary, in as much as when they are at the higheſt, yet they neuer exceede the latitude or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions of a coniecture. Fourthly, though in the ſenſe of my firſt concluſion we do not pray that all men generally, including the reprobate, may be ſaued; nor can giue thankes for the ſaluation of thoſe whom God ſaues not; yet <hi>for the temporall good of reprobates and all, whether ſpirituall or concerning their outward ſtate, we may both pray and giue thankes.</hi> The reaſon is, for God giues ſuch temporall things to the reprobate, and for his Churches good, to glorifie his Name, magnifie his liberality, make them without excuſe, and benefite his children: which being ends belonging to the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of Gods name in the wicked, we iuſtly pray for all that which may aduance them.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Touching prayer for our enemies, there lies no queſtion; our Sauiour ſo expreſly including it in the commandement touching prayer, and by his owne bleſſed example and the example of his deareſt ſeruants commending it to vs. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.21. <hi>Be not ouercome of euill, but ouercome euill with good.</hi> Philo, diſcourſing of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20569:12"/>Aarons Ephod which he put on whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he went to pray, ſaith it was <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>A repreſentation of the whole world:</hi> hauing in it all colours to repreſent all ſtates of people whatſoeuer. And in very deed we erre more groſly in nothing then in bearing malice, and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping mens names out of our prayers, as if our priuate affection were the calendar of euery mans ſaluation, when no man can rent himſelfe from his brother, but firſt he muſt rent himſelfe from Chriſt, who is the root whereon both he and his brother grow; as a branch on a tree, cannot ſeparate it ſelfe from the reſt of the branches, but firſt it muſt depart from the tree it ſelfe whereupon both it and all the other bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches grow. And therefore<note n="*" place="margin">Ephiph. ep. ad Ioan. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſol.</note> the Patriarke of Ieruſalem was vnwiſe to quarrell with Epiphanius becauſe he prayed for him; for Ephphanius anſwered, <hi>he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be ſo out of charitie with any man, that he would ſet him at nought, whom God had made:</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Lib. 1. de Cain &amp; Abel. cap. 9.</note> And Saint Ambroſe giues a good reaſon: <hi>Quia ſinguli orant pro omnibus, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam omnes orant pro ſingulis: When euery man prayes for all men, by this meanes all men pray for euery man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 But the ſpeciall perſons for whom particularly and namely we muſt pray, are <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>all in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> for Kings are Gods annointed: and as Tertullian<note n="q" place="margin">Ad Scap. cap. 2.</note> ſpeakes, <hi>Homines à Deo ſecundi, &amp; ſolo Deo minores: Next vnto God, and ſecond to none but God.</hi> The King,<note n="r" place="margin">Ad pop. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch. hom. 1.</note> ſaith Chryſoſtome, <hi>hath no Peere vpon earth, but is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: the head and top of all men that liue.</hi> Our neighbours of Rome now ſay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; that the Pope is the man: and Kings are but his officers, and vaſſals, to hold his ſtirrop, to beare his canopie, to hold him the baſon and ewre when he
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20569:12"/>waſhes, to be vſed or depoſed at pleaſure, as he ſhall ſee cauſe. This is that which the late Councell of Lateran in Rome called <hi>Regale Pontificium Romanorum genus: The roiall race of our Roman Biſhops.</hi> They call him that now is Paulus Quintus, <hi>Vice-deus, Reipub. Chriſtianae Monarcha, Pontificiae omnipotentiae aſſertor inuictiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. The vice-God and Monarch of the Chriſtian world, and the inuincible defender of the Papal omnipotencie.</hi> But let them alone; he is Antichriſt for his labour, whom Saint Paule ſayes, we ſhall know by this, that he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Beyond all Auguſteïty and them that are called Gods;</hi> as Kings, by Gods owne mouth are. S. Paul affirmes that to be <hi>the higheſt power which beares the ſword. Rom.</hi> 12. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore himſelfe<note n="ſ" place="margin">Act. 25.11.</note> 
               <hi>appealed</hi> to it. Optatus, againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts,<note n="t" place="margin">Lib. 3. contr. Parmen.</note> ſaith, <hi>Super Imperatorem non eſt niſi Deus, qui fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Imperatorem, there is none aboue the King but God that made the King.</hi> And with Kings muſt be ioyned <hi>all that are in authoritie;</hi> Peeers, Iudges, Magiſtrates, Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of State, Captaines of warre: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. All that are <hi>eminent,</hi> or haue any ſtroke in the gouernment. For they alſo may do good or hurt: for<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 41.43.</note> Ioſeph was the King of Egypts right hand: and they cried in the ſtreetes <hi>Abrech,</hi> for he was <hi>Pater patriae, A tender father</hi> to his countrey, and preſerued it in time of extremitie. Though Achitophel, and Shebnah, and Symmachus, and Stephen Gardiner, were not ſuch. For though good Kings neuer ſo willingly, as the Sunne, yeeld their light and comfort to the State, yet bad perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and vnder them, not louing the Goſpell nor iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but aiming at their owne priuate ends, like clouds or malignant ſtarres, may come betweene and hinder
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20569:13"/>the influence. Beſides, their example drawes like Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant; and their integritie is ſo needfull, that vnder the beſt Princes that euer were, that part of the State hath alway droopt and withered that bad officers haue med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled with. As on the contrarie, the vertue of the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Magiſtrate hath oftentimes qualified the errours and diſtempers of violent tyrants: as we may perceiue in the gouernement of Iehoaſh of Iuda,<note n="u" place="margin">2. Reg. 12.2</note> of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>He did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord all the dayes wherein Iehoiadah the Prieſt inſtructed him.</hi> This is the reaſon why the Church muſt pray for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>all in authoritie</hi> vnder them.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Learne here, that gouernement and eminency is of God, by his owne ordinance, for the benefite of mankind, and maintenance of ciuill ſocietie: elſe the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle would not haue tied vs to <hi>pray</hi> for them. Yea he ſaith expreſly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be are ordained of God;</hi> therefore God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them his owne names and titles, and ſets them in a throne like himſelfe: And<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> the Diuell, making an offer to Chriſt, that he would giue him <hi>All the kingdomes of the world,</hi> promiſed more then he had either right or power to performe. But here we muſt diſtinguiſh. There are foure things in a King and euery one that is in authoritie. Firſt, his <hi>perſon,</hi> wherein he partakes in the common nature of all other men, and liues and dies like them. Secondly, his <hi>power and royall dignitie.</hi> This is of God, whoſoeuer he be that hath it, whether a good Prince or a Tyrant: a Nero or a Conſtantine, one or other. Thirdly, his <hi>coming to his power.</hi> This al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is of God, when it is by lawful meanes, without vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation, elſe not. For he that ordaines the power, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20569:13"/>not the vſurpation of it. Fourthly, the <hi>vſe of this power,</hi> which being iuſt, and godly, and right, is alſo of God: but the abuſe of it by tyrannie or idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or iniuſtice, for example, is not ſo; for God allowes no power to ouerrule his owne Law. Our Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts therefore, and ſuch as are enemies to Monarchie, and all conſpirators, Aſſaſines, rebelles, and turbulent perſons, are beaſts, and enemies to Gods ordinance and to nature. For, ſaith Philo, <hi>He that liues vnder a law is a citizen of the world:</hi> the reaſon whereof he giues, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>He rules his actions according to the rule of nature.</hi> For albeit the Magiſtrate ſometimes ſtep into his place and vſe it vnlawfully, yet ſtill the place is of diuine ordinance, and the meanes to reforme what is amiſſe, is ſtill to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>all in authoritie.</hi> And not onely the King himſelfe is of God, but all the eminency and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of authoritie that is vnder him, his Nobles, his Councellers, his Iudges, his Magiſtrates, his Officers, his Courts, are all of God; to maintaine his State and royaltie, and to manage the affaires of the Common-wealth, which one man cannot do: and it is but a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage and popular humour to backbite or deſpiſe this <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency</hi> in whom ſoeuer. Thoſe rhymes, <hi>When Adam delued and Eue ſpan, &amp;c.</hi> were liker to be made in Wat Tylers campe, then any where elſe; and the practiſe of Libelling againſt Magiſtrates and great perſons, at this day, that neither the liuing can walke, nor the dead ſleepe, cannot be iuſtified. If any thing be amiſſe, there is cauſe rather of ſorrow then laughter, and it is fitter to pray, then to lay our heads together at a ſcurrilous Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quill: which tending to nothing but the bringing of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20569:14"/>into contempt and diſgrace, the end may be the ouerthrow of all at the laſt, when nothing is more dangerous in a State, then for Stateſmen to loſe their reputation: and the Stage and Poet, with ieaſtes and Satyres to deride ſinne, which by the Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church is grauely and ſeuerely to be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. It is true indeed that among the Greekes, <hi>in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri Comoedia</hi> the perſons of men were taxed: but they were Barbarians whom Chriſtians muſt not imitate; and the Magiſtrates thereby were diſgraced, and the rude people armed againſt them to the ruine of the beſt men, as we haue examples in Socrates and others, and therefore the beſt States put them all downe.</p>
            <p n="12">12 I come now to the laſt point of my text: which is, the thing prayed for, or the end why we pray for Kings, <hi>That we may leade a quiet and peaccable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie.</hi> In which words he names the thing with the conditions thereof. The thing is <hi>peace,</hi> the conditions are peace with <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> peace with <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie,</hi> in their latitude: <hi>All godlineſſe, all honeſtie.</hi> For peace without theſe things is no good or durable peace, but will deceiue the State that truſteth to it. <hi>Is it peace?</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. Reg. 9.22</note> ſaith Iehoram; but Iehu anſwered, <hi>What peace ſo long as the whoredomes of Iezabel and her witch-crafts remaine?</hi> We muſt therefore pray for <hi>peace</hi> with <hi>godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>honeſtie.</hi> This peace hath two degrees in the text: the firſt is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Publike quietneſſe,</hi> when the State is ſecured; neither wars nor garboiles, nor faction, nor conſpiracies, troubling it. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinus: <hi>Quietneſſe is the ſecuritie</hi> of the State <hi>from feare.</hi> The next is, <hi>peace &amp; tranquillity</hi> of euery mans priuate ſtate, when no ſtorme beating the publike, he liues at
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:20569:14"/>reſt in his priuate, and hath <hi>Vſum fructum communis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, The vſe and profite of the publike peace.</hi> An image wherof we haue in the dayes of Solomon:<note n="b" place="margin">1. Reg. 4.25</note> 
               <hi>They dwelt confidently euery man vnder his vine, and vnder his fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, from Dan to Beerſhebah.</hi> The want whereof gaue occaſion to a ſeruant of the Emperour Adrians, when he died, to write vpon his graue ſtones; <hi>Here he lies that died an old man and yet liued but ſeuen yeares;</hi> becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was out of his infancie, all the reſt of his life was beaten with labour and vnquietneſſe. The <hi>godlineſſe</hi> mentioned is the true faith, and right ſeruice and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God by true religion, when the ſame is nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the State: as in the dayes of thoſe Kings that put downe the groues and altars built to Baal. <hi>Honesty</hi> ſuppoſes euery vertue that maintaines ciuill ſocietie, and gouerns the outward life of the ſubiect: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie whereof is riot, diſorder, vnſeemlineſſe in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Theſe are the things to be aimed at in gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and for the obtaining whereof we muſt pray and giue thankes for <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>all in authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13 Note firſt, that the beſt and principalleſt things that can betide any people, is, the maintenance of <hi>true religion</hi> and <hi>godlineſſe,</hi> and the preſeruation of <hi>peace</hi> and outward <hi>honeſtie</hi> in the State: the Apoſtle requiring that we pray for theſe things <hi>firſt of all;</hi> as that which all men mut procure to the vttermoſt of their power: and which being obtained, God in this life, giues no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſſing. Our nation therfore poſſeſſing theſe things in ſo ample manner, muſt confeſſe that God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>richt it with his greateſt mercies, and made it moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, and giuen vnto in all that for the which he firſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained gouernement: of which point I ſhall ſay more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20569:15"/>in that which followeth.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Note againe, how the Magiſtrate, and others of eminencie, muſt aduance theſe things and procure them. Firſt in their owne perſons, and by their owne example, themſelues liuing grauely, religiouſly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. For if the end of prayer be that this may be in the State, how much more are the Stateſmen bound to aduance it in themſelues? It is a thing that great men and well borne, may be fitly take notice of, this day, as any day in the yeare; that the vſing of their pleaſures moderately and diſcreetly, and the compoſing of their manners and carriages, their ſtudies and example, to the maintenance of <hi>religion</hi> and <hi>honeſtie,</hi> will be very gratefull, this day, and well accord with the prayers of the Church. There is a fault this way, I wil touch it, but ſoftly: Many gentlemen and eminent perſons, ſpecially of the younger ſort, too much neglect that godlineſſe and gouernement which, by their meanes, another day, when they are in <hi>authoritie,</hi> they ſhould ſee main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in others. Lightneſſe of carriage, want of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ignorance in the lawes, cuſtomes and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the countrey, ſlackneſſe, or poſſible, auerſneſſe in religion, abandoning themſelues ouer to ſpending and ſenſuality: and for one particular, immoderate drinking: are euill diſpoſitions to eminencie, and will make them both vnable to maintaine the publike good, and vnfit to gouerne others. <hi>Nostíne hos,</hi> ſaith Pliny, <hi>qui omnium libidinum ſerui, eos puniunt quos imitantur? Haue you not ſeene thoſe who being the ſeruants of euery ſinne, yet puniſh that in others, which themſelues imitate? Mendacia fallax Damnat, &amp; in moechos gladium diſtringit adulter,</hi> was the complaint of Proſper: that is to ſay; when liers
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20569:15"/>were to be cenſured by deceiuers, and adulterers to be puniſhed by wantons. It was but a hard ſhift that a city in Spain was glad to vſe for the redreſſing of ſuch a like matter. Ludouicus Viues makes the report. The young Nobles and gentlemen, diuerſe of them, were fallen from the grauitie and honour of their anceſtors: they followed prodigalitie and lightneſſe; they were vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the lawes, and knew little Art, or militarie diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; euery one had his miſtris, and ſpend his time in courting her: bankets, reuels, dancing, amarouſneſſe, was their ſtudie. Great gallants they were, and that was all: which the ancient Magiſtrates obſeruing, thought, what will become of the countrey which theſe muſt gouerne when we are dead? They dealt with the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, on whom they ſaw they depended; their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Ladies, all the young gentlewomen; and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the inconuenience, required their helpe, and gaue them inſtruction: which they following effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, recouered the gentlemen. They repelled from their fauour all that were fantaſticall, ſent them to their bookes; aduiſed them to Armes, grauitie, ſobrietie, nobleneſſe: and fauouring none that were vaine, they wrought wonders, and ſecured the State; that theſe men proued as honourable and ſeruiceable in the ſame, as any of their anceſtors that were before them. I told you this was but a hard ſhift, yet was it the beſt they had; and would we had Ladies and gentlewomen to do as much for vs, when Biſhops and Preachers, and ſage examples of our State cannot do it.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Secondly, the Magiſtrates muſt maintaine ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill <hi>honeſtie</hi> in others alſo that liue vnder them. For, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>ſuch as do euill</hi> are threatned; for <hi>the Magiſtrate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20569:16"/>beares not the ſword in vaine, but is Gods minister to take vengeance on them.</hi> I need not ſtand to proue that which no man denies: onely they which know they ſhould do it, either do it negligently, or are outfaced that they dare not do it. Who ſeeth not that whoredome, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, ſwearing, quarrelling, and roaring (pittie we ſhoud be inforced to name ſuch things in this place) are ſo common, that ſcarce is there left in the ſtreetes, either <hi>religion,</hi> or <hi>honeſtie, godlineſſe</hi> or <hi>ciuilitie?</hi> But drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is now ſo taken vp through the whole kingdome, that the Germanes, I heare, are like to loſe their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? There was in Rome a ſtreete called <hi>Vicus Sobrius: The Sober ſtreete,</hi> becauſe there was neuer an alehouſe in it; which is hard to be ſaid of any ſtreete in England. I heard my ſelfe, not long ſince, the principall Magiſtrate of this Cittie, that then was, in an open ſpeech tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the bleeding ſins, and ſwelling ſores, (ſo, as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, he called them of the Cittie) and ſo tenderly exhort to amendement, that I well perceiued many things to be diſcouered that could not ſo eaſily be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. And yet the Magiſtrate muſt not be wearie for all that, when the prayers of the Church continually attend vpon him; and if, by all endeuour poſſible, this one ſinne of drinking could be put downe, the publike <hi>honeſtie</hi> of our nation would the eaſilier be maintained. Now, all ouer the land, the Iuſtice of peace is milde, and the drunkard merry, which two, you know, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend no ſinne. I will tell you a ſtorie in Athenaeus of an alehouſe that came to be called The ſigne of the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vpon this occaſion. The roaring-boyes meeting at a houſe, dranke ſo long that their braines being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20569:16"/>they thought all that was about them to be ſea, and the roome where they ſate a Gally, ſo toſſed with waues that they feared drowning; and therefore, as men in danger of ſhipwracke, they threw all things that came to hand out of the window into the ſtreete, pots, plate and furniture, to lighten the ſhip: which being taken vp &amp; carried away by ſuch as came by, the Magiſtrate next morning comes to puniſh them for the diſorder: but they, hauing not yet ſlept out their drinke, anſwered him, That it was better to caſt all into the ſea, then the Gally, wherein they were, ſhould be ſunke, and ſo many braue gentlemen be caſt away; and while the Magiſtrate wondred at their drunken imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, another, creeping from vnder the table where he had lien all the night, replied, thinking the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates to haue bene gods of the ſea; And I, ô ye Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, for feare laid me downe vnder the hatches: which diſtemper of theirs the officers perceiuing, went their way, and forgiuing them, bad, Do ſo no more: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they all gaue this thankes; If euer we eſcape this ſtorme, and get ſafe to land, we vow you ſtatues, and will ſet vp your images in our countrey as to our ſauiours. This ſtorie is a patterne of the behauiour which our drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards vſe, and the manner how it is puniſht abroad in the countrey; when they are preſented, they anſwer for themſelues ſome flegmaticke conceit of ſwimming in the ſea, that reliſhes of the broth; and the Magiſtrate bids, Do no more ſo: and ſo the drunkard in honour of the Iuſtice, makes his image for ſauing him, and writes vpon it, Good-ale neuer wanted a friend vpon the bench.</p>
            <p n="16">16 There is as much to be ſaid of drinking healths,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20569:17"/>but I want time, nor greatly care I what any man can pleade for it: one Saint Ambroſe is more to me; and one diſcourſe of his, <hi>De potu ad aequales calices,</hi> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching drinking healths, more moues me, then all the health maintainers in this Citie: whom I do moſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreate to reade ouer and ouer, the 13. and 17. Chapters of his booke, called <hi>De Elia &amp; Ieiunio:</hi> where he ſhall not onely ſee the very image of our times; <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus etiam pro ſalute Imperatoris: Let vs drinke Health to the Emperour,</hi> but heare the holy Biſhop ſo inueigh againſt it, that the grauity and bended browes of ſo great a Prelate were able to make the cup fall out of the greateſt Barons hand in England.<note n="*" place="margin">Auent.</note> The Emperour Aurelian was ill troubled to finde out one Bonoſus to quaffe with the German Ambaſſadour, who yet was derided for his labour, and commonly called, <hi>Not a man, but a drunken pitcher filled with wine.</hi> Our time affoords ſtore of theſe, whom no exerciſe can pleaſe without drinking, like the German mentioned by Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, who hearing a ſolemne Tilting at the Court ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany, cried out, <hi>O valeant ludi quibus nemo bibit: Farewell the game where there is no drinking.</hi> Let all men remember their end, and the terrible ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they ſhal, one day, make to him that hath ſaid it:<note n="o" place="margin">Eſ. 5.22. Habb. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be to them that are ſtrong to drinke, and giue their companions drinke that they may ſee their nakedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17 Let me inſiſt vpon a word more that is in my text: <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> of religion. Wherein no doubt, our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle deſires Gods bleſſing vpon Kings for this cauſe principally, that the true faith of Chriſt may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and hereſie ſuppreſſed. This is agreed vpon at all hands, that I neede not ſpend time in prouing it.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20569:17"/>
               <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12. He wiſheth they were <hi>cut off that trouble</hi> the Church: and Irenaeus reports the preciſeneſſe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the Chriſtians of thoſe times, to haue bin ſuch, <hi>Vt ne verbo tenus communicarent alicui eorum qui adulterauerat veritatem:</hi> That they would not ſo much as talke, or in words communicate with any that had violated the truth. For, him that is <hi>an hereticke auoide,</hi> ſaith our Apoſtle, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. Our countreymen Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manized and Ieſuited, haue filled the world with out-cries againſt our State, for ſupreſſing them, and making lawes againſt their religion. What they ſay, and how they exclaime, and what they conſpire about this matter, I cannot now ſtand to rehearſe; but if their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie and ſuperſtition be not expelled, how ſhall your faith ſtand? What ſecurity ſhall Sarah and her ſonne Iſaak haue in the houſe, if Hagar and her brat be not beaten out of doores? I will play at ſhort weapons with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; come to the point. PAPISTRY CAN STAND NEITHER WITH PEACE NOR PIETIE: THE STATE THEREFORE THAT WOVLD HAVE THESE THINGS, HAD IVST CAVSE TO SVP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PRESSE IT. Touching our <hi>Peace,</hi> it hath not bene violated in our State theſe many yeares, but by them: nor ſcarce in any State Chriſtian, ſince Charles the Great his time, but the Pope and his miniſters haue had a hand in it.<note n="*" place="margin">Pet. de Vin. lib. 1. ep. 31.</note> It was the complaint of the noble Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke the ſecond, <hi>Reuera Imperialis authoritas Papali ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per impugnatur inuida: The Papal enuy hath alway blasted the authoritie of Kings.</hi> And I challenge all the Ieſuites this day in England, let them giue an inſtance of any kingdome in the Chriſtian world theſe eight hundred yeares that hath not complained of the Pope inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medling,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20569:18"/>and croſſing their peace. But I will ſhew them that a great part of the moſt grieuous tragedies that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fell out in any kingdome, whether the combuſtion, or the ouerthrow of the State, or the murder of the king, haue bene contriued by them; and ſo long as there is a book to be ſold in this Church-yard, or we can keep our libraries from their purging, it wil be iuſtified by due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord.<note n="*" place="margin">Niceph. Gregor.</note> He was a great King that put one to death for but wearing his Crowne in his owne preſence: he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his barge, and his Crowne falling into the water, the barge man ſwom after it, and onely put it on his head as he ſwam till he recouered the barge: the King gaue him a talent for ſauing it, but cut off his head for wearing it. Would God theſe men had done no more but reached at the crowne to ſaue it, but we know they haue indeuoured to ſteale it: and if authority cut them not ſhorter, they will whenſoeuer occaſion ſerues, ſinke and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p n="18">18 I will ſay nothing of their priuate turbulencie, nor what good neighbours they are at home in the country where they rule the houſe that harbors them, &amp; ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the goodwife or Lady thereof. I will onely touch their ſawcineſſe with the Crowne, that which our State droops and bleeds vnder. Who is ſuch a ſtranger in our State, that he knowes not their refuſall of an oath one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for allegeance and ciuill obedience? their ſuing for diſpenſation, and their open conteſtations with his Maieſty and the State about it, the Pope with his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Conſiſtorie maintaining them? Saint Auſtin ſayes, <hi>We distinguiſh betweene the eternall God, and the temporall Lord; yet we obey the temporall Lord for his ſake that is the eternall God.</hi> And all Antiquity confeſſed (I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20569:18"/>vſe the very words of Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenius, and Theophylact) that <hi>were he an Apostle, a Prophet, an Euangeliſt, a Biſhop, a Priest, a Monke: Siue quisquis tandem fuerit, of what cloath ſoeuer his Coate be made,</hi> the King is aboue him. Strabo tels of a High prieſt in Pontus, that ware a Crowne, whoſe ſubiects were called <hi>Hieroduli,</hi> whom he ruled with Kingly authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but he was a Pagan, and ſtill the King was his Lord. The Pope affects this prehemience, and would haue all the world to be his <hi>Hieroduli:</hi> he and his crew will be Pagans, Donatiſts, Anabaptiſts, what you will ſo they be no ſubiects.<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 22.25.</note> Chriſt told his Diſciples, Peter and all, <hi>The Kings of the Gentiles exerciſe Lordſhip ouer them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi> The Pope and Papiſts will exerciſe it, and turne the text, <hi>Kings exerciſe Lordſhip o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their ſubiects, and you ſhal exerciſe it ouer Kings, &amp; not be ſubiect.</hi> This point of ſubiection lies in their bones.<note n="*" place="margin">Ph. Camer.</note> There was ſometime in Gaunt, as diuerſe of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates were ſitting on a bench in the ſtreet, a Begger, who paſſing by craued their almes, &amp; complained, that he had a ſecret diſeaſe lying in his bones, and running all ouer his body, which he might not for ſhame diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to them; they moued with pittie, gaue him each of them ſomewhat, and he departed. One more curious then the reſt, bad his man follow him, and learne, if he could, what that ſecret diſeaſe ſhould be: who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to him, and ſeeing nothing outwardly vpon him, but wel to looke at; Forſooth, quoth the Begger, that which paines me you ſee not, I have a diſeaſe lying in my bones, and all my parts, that I cannot worke: ſome call it <hi>Sloth</hi> and ſome <hi>Idleneſſe.</hi> Our Ieſuited Papiſts haue a diſeaſe that holds them much like this of the Begger;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20569:19"/>they cannot be ſubiect; to looke at outwardly you ſhall diſcerne nothing, for they are cloſe: but there creeps all ouer their body, through euerie ioynt, and is ſetled in the marrow, a Lordly humour, that they cannot obey, nor vnderſtand themſelues to be the Kings ſubiects any longer then the Pope will haue them. Some Phiſitians extenuate the nature and danger of the diſeaſe, but the begger of Gaunt was not ſo bad, nor ſo hard to cure; and we ſee, when Phiſitians haue done the vttermoſt, it turns at laſt to treaſon and rebellion; that he which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires the Kings ſafety, muſt pray for ſtronger phiſicke then yet hath bene giuen, to purge this humour: though for my owne part I thinke, the phiſicke ſtrong enough if the ſturdy beggers were made to drinke it and, law were backt with execution.</p>
            <p n="19">19 What wofull treaſons did they contriue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that bleſſed Lady our gracious Elizabeth that now is gone? what rebellions and inuaſions did they kindle? what miſchiefe had they in their heads againſt her? And now ſhe is gone (Ah the ſacred name of Chriſtian piety where art thou buried, that we might viſite thy monument!) how barbarouſly haue theſe <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcrorum effoſſores</hi> raked and digged into her graue, and railed vpon her royall name? whom ſtrangers haue come from far to ſee, as ſhe of Saba did to ſee So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon? forreiners reuerenced, ſubiects doted vpon, all Princes liuing admired, themſelues openly flattered, and for the time fawned vpon? Ah bleſſed Lady how did God, by thy hands, that which the potenteſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the world could hardly reach to? Honour held her State within thy Crowne, Maieſtie ſprang in thy breaſt, thy heart was fild with pietie, thy hands with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20569:19"/>thy lap with plentie, thy throne with iuſtice: thou lieſt not buried in the cold earth, but in the liuing harts of all that knew thee; that which the peerleſſe Ladies of the former world had ſeuerally, thou hadſt alone: <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cida, Pulcheria, Galla, Theodelind, Eudocia, Palaelogina;</hi> of whom<note n="*" place="margin">Niceph. Gregot.</note> it is ſaid, that with the bounty and admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her ſex, as with a net ſhe fiſht, and caught, &amp; drew vnto her the opinions of all men; and yet there is found a generation that curſe thy name: as there was a people that had a daily ceremony, to go out of dores, and with their face into the Eaſt to curſe the Sun that gaue them light, and by his influence preſerued them.</p>
            <p n="20">20. His gracious Maieſty ſpeeds no better; let their curſed writings, and baſe ſpeeches of him, and all other practifes againſt him, be laide aſide: and remember but the POWDER TREASON, the vttermoſt point of all villany, beyond which it is <hi>terra incognita,</hi> no man can deuiſe what ſhould be between Hell and it. The Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of the Legend, hearing all the diuels in Hell, as he thought, together on the other ſide of the wall, lifting, and blowing, and groning, as if they had bene remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the world, deſired God to let him ſee what they were doing; and they were but lifting at a feather: had not the Hermite come in. they would haue feathered ſuch an arrow, as ſhould haue ſtrooke through the heart of the child yet vnborne. They ſay there is a bird, that, when men are at ſacrifice, takes fire from the altar, and burnes their houſes; theſe are the birds of that feather, that can finde no fire to burne our State but what is kindled on their very altars, and the deareſt ceremonies of their religion. Religion, ſacraments, prayer, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt things they haue, and God himſelfe, are applied to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20569:20"/>execute the diuell and his Vicars curſed will. Thuanus writes that the Pope cauſed the maſſacre of Paris (what time, in diuerſe parts of France were murdered aboue 60000 perſons) to be painted in his pallace; it ſhould ſeeme, <hi>Ad perpetuam rei memoriam;</hi> leſt ſo extreme wickedneſſe ſhould be forgotten. So no doubt ſhould this Powder worke haue bene painted by it, if it had not miſcarried: ſaue that no Art could haue imitated the confuſion, no colour haue repreſented ſo barbarous crueltie. What ſtaine could ſhadow the bloud of ſo royall Princes? what red were ſufficient to paint the bloud of ſo many and noble Chriſtians? what blacke, the darkneſſe of that day? what azure the vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fire? what deuice, what inuention could haue expreſſed the wofull crie of the innocent, and the infernall noiſe of the blow? If they were men, why did they worke like diuels? if chriſtian men, let me ſpeake to them in the wordes of Saint Cyprian: <hi>Quid facit in pectore Chriſtiano Luporum feritas, canum rabies, ſaeuitia beſtiarum, venenum lethale ſerpentum? How came into the breaſt of Chriſtians the rage of Wolues, the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of dogs, the cruelty of beaſts, the deadly poyſon of veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſerpents? Cum ſitis impij, crudeles, homicidae, inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani, non amplius eritis Chriſtiani:</hi> ſaith Lucifer Calazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus, of the Arians: <hi>When you are become impious, cruel, murderers, without humanity, you ſhall no longer be called Chriſtians.</hi> Yet theſe men are made our ghoſtly fathers, and hearken a little; and take the meaſure of them that cry themſelues, as loud as oiſter-women in the ſtreets, The Apoſtles ſucceſſours. Ouer and beſides that I haue already ſaid, and all the reſt, they haue violated our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20569:20"/>Churches, threatned the Stateſman, aſſaulted the offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, reſcued the malefactour, broken the priſons, ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered our cattell; theſe fiftie yeares together trauelled of nothing but the deſtruction of their deareſt countrey that bred and bare them. O earth, earth, earth, couer not this impietie, and let their wickedneſſe finde no place; ô heauens aboue reueale it; ô heauen and earth, and all you creatures, were it poſſible you had any ſence of our complaint, beare witneſſe of it: Prieſts are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into hangmen, maſſing into maſſacring, ghoſtly fathers into bloudly murtherers, Colledges of Friars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dennes of Aſſaſines. Alas for the infamie of our age to beare the date of ſuch impieties. But thou ô bleſſed Trinitie, the ſole infuſer of grace, who haſt kindled the feeling of all this wickedneſſe, as a fire in my bones, moue the hearts of our ſeduced countreymen, open their eyes, and leade them into the wayes of peace and godlines: and as for Rome that workes nothing but the ruine of thy Church and Goſpell; <hi>Remember O Lord the children of Edom in the day of Ieruſalem, how they haue cried againſt thy Sanctuarie, Downe with it, downe with it, euen to the foundation, O daughter Babylon, who one day ſhalt be waſted and deſtroyed; happie ſhall he be that rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thee as thou haſt ſerued vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 There is much to be ſaid touching their reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; their turbulencie troubles <hi>peace</hi> no more then their hereſies corrupt <hi>religion:</hi> no time now to inſiſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the point: this muſt be tried by our publike wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and diſputations, if any man will do it exactly. If the ſeuerall points of their faith, and the articles of their NEW CREED were euer taught or beleeued in the ancient Church, or otherwiſe came into the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20569:21"/>world then by the ſtrength of humane wit, fer the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancing of the Pope and his Clergies greatneſſe, why haue they purged ſo many ancient books, coined ſo many writings, and alowed nothing to be authenticall but what the Pope agrees to? and<note n="*" place="margin">Regula in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>failibilis ad firmandum vnam fidem, eſt fummus Pontiſex Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus: &amp; omnes atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi fidei vlti matèreſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vuntur in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam <hi>Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin. Corol. pag.</hi> 251.</note> made him the ſole rule of all mens faith and conſcience? And I greatly care not what any man perſwades himſelfe to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Our Church at this day, and euer ſince the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of religion, hath had as learned Diuines able to iudge of theſe things, as the Pope and his abettors in all their nations haue any to oppoſe againſt them: and which is Gods ſpeciall fauour to vs, we haue a King who with his own mouth and pen can iuſtifie as much as his lawes maintaine, againſt the beſt of them all. Yet it lies not all on the point of learning neither: Sauana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola truly<note n="a" place="margin">De Ord. ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. lib. 3.</note> ſaith, <hi>Veritas Scripturae puritate cordis &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na illuſtratione magis addiſcitor quàm vi ingenij aut ſtudij humani exercitio: The truth of the Scripture is ſooner lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by pure hearts enlightened from aboue, then by the ſtrength of wit or exerciſe of humane ſtudie.</hi> What it is that drawes ſo many to papiſtry, and filles the land with ſo many Seminarie Prieſts, we know well enough: the Friar long ſince diſcouered it to his nouice, when he told him the aduantage that ghoſtly fathers had ouer the lay people: We keepe their counſell, they keepe none of ours: we haue part of their lands, they haue none of ours: we haue charitie towards their wiues, they towards none of ours: they bring vp our children, we none of theirs. A Marqueſſe of Brandenberg was wont to ſay, that he had three Monaſteries in his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey that were ſo many miracles. One of the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi> who had abundance of corne, and yet had no land
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20569:21"/>to ſow: Another of the <hi>Franciſcans,</hi> who were full of money, and yet receiued no rents: The third of <hi>Saint Thomas,</hi> whoſe Monkes had many children, and yet had no wiues, Theſe ſpeeches were in their time pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vttered, but all the world knowes the morall to be true: and ſo I leaue them and will end my text, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate you to retire to our publike gratulation.</p>
            <p n="22">22 If our Apoſtle would haue <hi>Prayer and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing for Kings and all in authoritie,</hi> then when Nero was Emperour, ſuch a tyrant and monſter that<note n="*" place="margin">See Hieron in Dan. 11. Seuer. Sulp. ſacr hiſt. lib. 2. Auguſt. De Ciuit. lib. 20. cap. 19.</note> diuers held him to be Antichriſt; and euery Magiſtrate then liuing was a deadly perſecutor of the Goſpell; how deeply are we bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to giue God thanks for our times, wherein we enioy ſo gracious a Gouernor? I ſpeake of one of the beſt and greateſt Princes that the Church of God hath lightly had, and this land, yet, neuer had any greater: and therfore my ſelfe being of ſo ſmall faculty and ſtrait conceit, I muſt intreate you, in the phraſe of Philo, <hi>To behold the image of a great mountaine in a ſmall ring:</hi> To conceiue the worth of a good King in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row words of an vnskilfull ſpeaker; when the mercies of God beſtowed on vs, in, and by him, I freely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, are higher and greater then I can meaſure. Were I a <hi>Pacatus,</hi> a <hi>Claudian,</hi> a <hi>Mamertinus,</hi> that ſo nobly ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out the praiſe of their Emperours: had I the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and faculty of an <hi>Euſebius,</hi> an <hi>Amberoſe,</hi> a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzen,</hi> a <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> I would ſay as much of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie as they ſaid of Conſtantine, Theodoſius, or Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian. For,<note n="*" place="margin">Caſſiod. var. lib. 9. ep. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Stipendium &amp; Tyranno penditur, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatio non niſi bono Principi: Men pay tribute to Tyrants, but commendations are due to good Princes,</hi> and the leaſt reward we can yeeld them. He is vnthankful that is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20569:22"/>of a benefite, vnthankfull that requites it not; vnthankfull that denies it; but moſt vnthankfull that diſſembles it. Though we cannot requite the mercy of God, yet we will neither forget nor diſſemble it.</p>
            <p n="23">23 It was Gods owne immediate doing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint him ouer vs, when the ſinnes of our nation rather cried for vengeance then deſerued ſo happie gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and the vttermoſt that the wit of enemies and malice of Satan could do, was not wanting to make diuerſion. The manifold dangers from which God hath deliuered him, euen from his cradle, are ſo many pledges of his loue to vs: for they ſhall not miſcarrie whom God protects. Dauid was grieuouſly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: Ioaſh his life ſought by his owne grand-mother Athaliah.<note n="o" place="margin">Phot. bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. pag. 30.</note> Conſtantine being a youth in Diocleſians Court, by the craft of Maximinus, was trained to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate with a Lion.<note n="*" place="margin">Euagr. lib. 5. cap. 21.</note> When Mauritius was an infant, his mother ſaw a Faerie oftentimes to pull him out of his cradle, and offer to deuoure him. Queene Elizabeths dangers you all know. So that what we haue is Gods entire mercie againſt the malice of men and euil angels. That day right was giuen to the ſucceſſion, which is no ſmall bleſſing: For,<note n="*" place="margin">Wiſd. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Baſtard plants take no rooting.</hi> Two mightie nations that ſprang out of one wombe, but had bene deuided euer ſince they were borre, which is 2500. yeares, were vnited: the benefite whereof, if it be well purſued, will be ſimply the greateſt that can belong to both the states, if, as brothers they will ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from iniuries, and ſtriue which ſhall ouercome other in pietie and brotherly offices. There was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that we had before, but by his Maieſtie we haue it either enlarged or confirmed to vs, and by hope
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20569:22"/>of ſucceſſion in his iſſue, to our children after vs: Peace, Religion, Honour, Security: the beſt things and all that a State can deſire. The inconuenience is, that by long enioying them we diſccrne not their price: as the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians abounding with gold and pearle, trucke them for pinnes and glaſſes. Had we liued a while as<note n="o" place="margin">Iud. 6.</note> Iſrael did vnder the Madianites, in holes &amp; caues of the earth for ſeare, had we taſted the times of our Baro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s war here in England: liued a while in Flanders vnder the D. of Alua; or in France the time of their ciuill warres, and taſted their maſſacres: or vnder the Spaniard in the Weſt Indies: or a while vnder the Turke in Natolia where he breeds his ſouldiers: or but at home vnder a Boner, and a Wincheſter, or a Spaniſh Inquiſition: our taſte would returne vnto vs, and we ſhould better know what we haue.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Touching Religion, and the gouernment of our Church, eſtabliſhed by his Highneſſe, there be many complaints made by our Browniſts &amp; their fauourers: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Simocatt. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>for diſcontented mindes are alway whining, and vpon ſmall occaſions vſe to multiply mountaines of complaints: and fill the world with their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity.</hi> A contemptible generation they, are and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy anſwer: yet I will ſay no more then is true; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is as purely taught &amp; maintained in England this day, as in any Church or nation in Europe, &amp; as much liberty allowed to preach it: and touching the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall gouernment by Biſhops which they ſo vellicate, I proteſt before God and man, it amaſeth me to ſee ſuch as can reade either the Scripture or Antiquity to carpe at it, when the Chriſtian world, for 1400 yeares after Chriſt, neuer ſaw any other gouernment. I will flatter</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:20569:23"/>
            <p>times ouer: thriſe with his weight in ſiluer, twiſe in gold, once in pearle, and vnions, and yet could not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. Oh that there had beene but one dram of his Highneſſe clemencie in thoſe hearts that were ſo inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable: who hath ſaued, &amp; pardoned more then (poſſible) hath ſtood with his owne ſafety. What can I ſpeake of his Learning, Eloquence, and gifts of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture worthy of the ſame! wherein I preſume his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt aduerſaries will not deny him to parallel, if not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede, all Princes liuing, &amp; to be equall to the learnedſt that haue gone before him. We haue heard him hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſaw him now lately in our Vniuerſities, in the middeſt of the learnedſt in all Profeſſions, ſpeaking &amp; diſcourſing with no leſſe iudgement and readineſſe of vtterance and conceit, then if it had bene his ordinary Profeſſion. How much adoe had many to refraine ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie teares for ioy to ſee a mightie and potent King, and Gods vicegerent vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, to bring al his State &amp; Roi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty with him into the ſchooles of the Prophets, &amp; there with ſuch humilitie and meekneſſe to ſit him downe among his poore ſubiects, and conuerſe with them in their owne facultie? Neuer was there in the world a greater Patron to Learning and learned men; there being few that excell in Learning and zeale for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, euen in forreine parts, but he hath ſome way made them beholding to him: his owne writings of all ſorts, but principally in the cauſe of Religion againſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, are ſuch as haue ennobled his Kingdome for euer and haue giuen more life and courage to vs all, then I may well with modeſty expreſſe: and time ſhall ſhew, thoſe writings will worke ſcuh effects againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth, that the ages to come ſhall him
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20569:23"/>Bleſſed. And for his conſtancy in the maintenance and propagation of religion, both at home and abroad, I am not the word and ſacrament? that ſcarce any priuate man heares more Sermons then himſelfe: that, in this reſpect, as much may be ſaid of his Court, as was ſaid of the Court of Theodoſius, that it was turned into an Oratorie for the daily ſeruice of God. And to aſſure vs of his entire heart, he hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deareſt pledges that he poſſibly could: againſt the Pope and his band he hath expoſed his Crowne, dignity, children, life; all he hath: what would we more? We know well enough how he hath bene laboured at home and abroad for toleration of Papiſtry: and how the Recuſants and their Patrons haue negotiated the buſineſſe: yet could they neuer nor ſhall they euer ſtirre him. That day he gaue the Noble Princeſſe, that gracious Ladie his daughter to the Palatine, he ſealed vs an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of his hand to teſtify his loue to religion; and make his affection thereunto known to all men. Go we yet forward to the reſt. How religiouſly and vertuouſly hath he cauſed the Prince his ſonne to be brought vp, whoſe education is ſuch, that I make a queſtion whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Biſhop in our kingdome be ſo religious and carefull in the education of his child? This we are ſure of; his Maieſtie cannot, in all that is vnder his hands, more gratifie the State, and the Church of God, and his poore ſubiects therein, then in this one thing, if the conſequence thereof be well conſidered and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the contrary. Let carping ſpirits and medling tongues, that hold it their chiefeſt libertie to ſcan Kings and take into their actions, containe themſelues: theſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20569:24"/>his vertues, and this loue which he hath ſhewed to State and Church, ſhall bind all godly hearts vnto him, and make them the tabernacle of his honour; when Papiſts and factions haue ſpet out their venime: whom I could charme wel enough if they were not deaffe Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Dauid commended Saul: the Spirit of God Dauid: the ancient Church could neuer ſatisfie it ſelfe in extolling Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, Gratian; and yet, if I liſted, I could picke quarrels to the beſt of them: and charge euery one of them with ſome particulars that his Maieſtie cannot be tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with.</p>
            <p n="26">26 Let vs haue an eye to the text. When God, by his gouernent, vpholds vnto vs Peace, Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Religion, Godlineſſe: praiſe God for the King, and ye praiſe him for all theſe things: Loue and ſerue the King, and ye loue and ſerue God that hath giuen you all. Let vs ſing a ſong of thankſgiuing to God for his mercies: Holy, holy, Lord God of hoaſts; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth are full of thy goodneſſe: thou haſt viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thy people, and ſhewed them thy ſaluation: thy bountie and thy mercie hath crowned them with glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and turned away the puniſhment of their ſinnes: and let vs ſay, with the people at the inauguration of Solomon,<note n="o" place="margin">1 Reg. 139.</note> 
               <hi>God ſaue the King:</hi> that vnder him we and our poſteritie may leade a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſſe and honeſtie. Vnto whom our God, one glorious, gracious, and immortall God, the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, be rendred againe and againe all honor and glory now and euermore. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20569:24"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT THE SPITTLE in London, vpon Eaſter Monday, 1613.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. TIM. 6.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Charge them that are rich in this world, that they be not high minded, nor truſt in vncertaine riches, but in the liuing God who giues vs richly all things to enioy: That they do good, that they be rich in good workes, readie to Diſtribute, willing to Communicate: Laying vp in ſtore for themſelues a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternall life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N which words the bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle inſtructs Timothy, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Epheſus, how to preach to great and wealthy men, and how to exhort them touching the vſe of their riches, that they may be ſaued. For it is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that as the poore imbraced the Goſpell, ſo many rich alſt. For, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.45. we reade of diuers that had faire <hi>poſſeſsions</hi> and much <hi>wealth;</hi> and 19.31. of ſome that were of the <hi>chiefeſt of Aſia,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued: for Epheſus, and all Aſia were full of wealth: and if there had bene none then, yet afterward, when the fulnes of the Gentiles ſhould come in, there would be many both great, and noble, and rich, and wealthy,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20569:25"/>that God would call into his Church, in all ages, and therefore he leaues this Scripture for them: to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and direct them in the vſe of their riches, and teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how to carrie themſelues, that, with their greatnes, they might alſo enioy the hope of eternall life; without which hope all worldly wealth and greatneſſe were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing worth. For, <hi>What ſhall it profite a man to winne the whole world, if he loſe his ſoule?</hi> ſaith our Sauiour. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.26. And as at a funeral dinner there are many gueſts and great cheere, but no mirth, becauſe he is dead that ſhould make it: ſo in the ſtate of riches there is great plenty and much abundance of outward things, but no fecuritie of mind, if they be not well vſed; becauſe that is wanting that ſhould giue it, the hope of ſaluation, and aſſurance of eternall life in the world to come. He had ſaid, a little before, verſe the ninth, that <hi>Such as will be rich fall into temptation and ſnares, and lusts, that plonge them into deſtruction;</hi> and that <hi>the deſire of money</hi> ſhould be <hi>auoided as the roote of all euill:</hi> The which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, leſt it ſhould be miſtaken, he expounds in this place; that his meaning is not ſimply to condemne the ſtate of rich men, as ſome do, but onely to forewarne them of the danger: that they poſſeſſe their riches, &amp; vſe them with that humilitie of mind, and thankfulneſſe to God, and readineſſe to do good, that they may make them a meanes to preferre themſelues thereby to the vndoubted hope of eternall life.</p>
            <p n="2">2 I know well, this doctrine, and very likely this text too, is often handled in this place, but that is no matter; the audience and occaſion will ſcarce admit any other. The Prieſts muſt walke, with the ſame Arke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their ſhoulders, euery day once, about the wals of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20569:25"/>Iericho for ſixe dayes together; and the ſeuenth day ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times: <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 6.3. The King of Iſrael beat the ground thrice, and the Prophet was angry that he beat it no oftener. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 13.18. The <hi>Sunne</hi> riſeth daily, yet no man is wearie of it. The bodie is nouriſhed, and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes cured, not ſo much with the varietie of meates and phyſicke, as with their goodneſſe and finneſſe. If it pleaſe God to giue me ſtrength, and you patience, the Text will ſerue well enough.</p>
            <p n="3">3 It containes a threefold admonition for the rich. Firſt, touching their mind, what to auoide: <hi>Not to be high minded, not to truſt in their riches, but in God.</hi> Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then touching the vſe of their wealth: <hi>That they do good, that they be rich in good workes, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate.</hi> Thirdly, touching the end why they muſt do this: <hi>That they may lay vp in ſtore, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, a good foundation againſt the time to come, that they may lay hold on eternall life.</hi> They may poſſeſſe their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but their riches muſt not poſſeſſe their minde. Then againe, they muſt not poſſeſſe their riches alone, but, as Gods ſtewards put in truſt, they muſt faithfully impart them to others. Then laſtly, they muſt ſo ſtore vp riches, that they ſtore vp withall a good conſcience, and ſo lay hold on theſe earthly things, that they loſe not the hold of better things in the life to come. Theſe are the particulars of the whole.</p>
            <p n="4">4 But firſt let it be noted how he propounds this doctrine: <hi>Charge them that are rich in this world.</hi> He condemnes not riches, nor diſallowes their vſe, but onely bids Timothy admoniſh ſuch as haue them to be <hi>humble minded.</hi> He binds no man to renounce them, but to vſe them well, and to ioyne the riches of Gods
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20569:26"/>grace with them. There haue bene humours excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding buſie with riches and greatneſſe, and all property and dominion; that euery thing might be in common. The Councell of Dioſpolis charges Pelagius with this opinion, and made him recant it. But he was not the firſt. Niceph. lib. 9. cap. 16. ſaith of Euſtathius and his ſectaries, <hi>Quod locupletes extorres prorſus regno coeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe duxerunt:</hi> They held no wealthy man could be ſaued. In our times the Anabaptiſts plied this conceit: they made a booke, called <hi>Opus restitutionis,</hi> wherein they taught it violently. Hortenſius, in his ſtorie, tels ſtrange practiſes of theirs this way. But it is an abſurd humour, fit for none but banktouts and rebelles: when poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are giuen of God, and property is founded in the law of Nature: and againſt it Saint Auſtine, <hi>Ep.</hi> 89. <hi>q.</hi> 4. wittily obſerued, that <hi>Lazarus a poore man, ſate in heauen, in Abrahams boſome, that was a rich man.</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſaith, <hi>The rich and the poore meete together, and the Lord made them both. Prou.</hi> 22.2.</p>
            <p n="5">Note againe how the Apoſtle will haue Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and, by his example, the Miniſters of the Church, to to preach to the rich alſo, and the greateſt that liue; and ſo to preach, that they be not flattered and let alone in bad courſes: but <hi>charged</hi> and admoniſhed, if they ſhould chance to be <hi>high minded</hi> or vnthankful to God; for they are a portion of the flock, ouer which the holy Ghoſt hath made vs ouerſeers, and vnto whom the wil of God muſt be reuealed as well as the poore. And though they be greater then the Preacher, in this world, yet they are not greater then he that ſends the Preacher to them. <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Whatſoeuer I command thee thou ſhalt ſpeake. Be not afraid, I haue put my words into thy mouth.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20569:26"/>I haue ſet thee ouer nation; &amp; kingdomes:</hi> And <hi>Apo.</hi> 10. <hi>vlt. Thou muſt prophecy among the Nations, &amp; to many Kings.</hi> In the which reſpect Nazianz. ſayes of the Emperour himſelfe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>The Law of God hath ſubiected you to our Pulpits.</hi> Saint Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſayes, <hi>Siue quis Dux militiae ſit, fiue Praefectus, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Princeps diademate coronatus, maiorem illo potestatem habes: Whoſoeuer he be thou art aboue him: thou art the keeper of the flock, ſuffer none to defile the ſountaine of water whereof the Sheepe ſhould drinke, but repell them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 The rich and the mightie muſt note this, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers muſt obſerue it, that both ſides keepe euen quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Great men haue alway bene hard to deale with. <hi>Pride the rich mans coſin</hi> (ſo Bernard ſtiles it) fills them with ſtoutnes and preſumption. <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.21 <hi>I ſpake to thee in thy proſperity, but thou wouldſt not heare me, this hath bene thy manner.</hi> Whereby it comes to pas, that many times the Preacher by doing but his duty, by <hi>charging</hi> them that are <hi>Rich,</hi> fals into much trouble: not that the Poorer ſort are much better: for we finde as much Pride and Preſumption among them as with the Rich; but they want teeth and horns; <hi>The Sonnes of Zeruiah are too ſtrong for vs.</hi> All the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Paſtors of the Church in all ages haue found this by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And if the vpholding of Chriſts kingdome againſt the world and ſin, and the ſaluation of our ſoules, lay not vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon it, it were better for vs neuer to haue to do with a great man. The Shepheard hauing loſt a lambe out of his ſlock, made a vow to God, that if he might finde the theefe, hewould ſacrifice a Ram. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the purſuit he found a Lion preying vpon it, he made another vow, that if God would deliuer him from the Lions furie, he</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20569:27"/>
            <p>not giue way to Gods authoritie, but ſo vnthankfully draw pride from that which ſhould draw them to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble themſelues to God the more; it is iuſt with God to leaue them in the hands of vnprofitable teachers. An vnworthie thing no doubt, and ill befitting the maieſty of the Pulpit, for a Preacher to flatter any man, to trifle in his Sermons, or priuate exhortations, to ſow his ſeed in the eare, to hunt after his owne credite: not to deale, as farre as his facultie reaches, throughly: and yet the holy Ghoſt complaines of ſuch all ouer the Scripture. That a man may ſay of their preaching as a good wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth of Iriſh Harpes, <hi>Oculos paſcunt, aures onerant:</hi> It is better to ſee them then heare them. There is much delight to ſee their nimble fingring, how they runne in and out, and touch double and treble; but the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody is not much worth. And yet, they ſay, <hi>Saint Key<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wins Harpc is kept for a great relicke,</hi> as flattering and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball Preachers are now and then great relickes with worldly men. <hi>Quae otioſorum auribus placent, aegrotorum animis non proſunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saluianus: That which moſt tickles delicate eares, leaſt helpes diſeaſed ſoules.</hi> Let no man therefore, how great ſoeuer, carrie that minde, to haue the Preacher conceale any part of this <hi>charge:</hi> If you cannot amend your ſinne ſo ſoone as you ſhould, ô yet ſuffer vs to rebuke it, to touch it, to ſmite it: our doctrine and plaine dealing, in time, may be a meanes to helpe and heale you. You giue the Phiſitian leaue to tell you any diſeaſe that is in you bodie: your Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ier leaue to ſhew you any flaw that is in your ſtate; your horſekeeper telles ye the ſurfets of your horſe: your huntſman the ſurrances of your dogs: and muſt we onely diſſemble, and conceale from you the ſinnes of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20569:27"/>your ſoule? We will not do it: we will loue you, and pray for you, and honour your greatneſſe; but your ſinnes we will reproue, and what God hath bidden vs, we will <hi>charge</hi> you with. And this little booke that we hold in our hand, ſhall giue vs more true comfort then the following and fawning vpon all the greatneſſe of the world. Hitherto of the charge in generall.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Now I come to the particulars, and firſt he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhes them touching their minde. The foundation of all wel-doing muſt be laid in the heart; for, <hi>Prou.</hi> 4.23. <hi>thereout the whole life proceedeth.</hi> And <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.33. firſt, <hi>Make the tree good.</hi> This is the reaſon why the light of the Moone is variable and vnconſtant, ſometime more, and ſometime leſſe, and ſometime none at all, becauſe it is but borrowed; and this will make great men vnconſtant in their wel-doing, if the heart be not ſtabliſhed with grace, in it ſelfe; therefore Gods charge vnto them is, to begin with the heart. This charge is ſet downe, firſt negatiuely: <hi>Not to be high minded: not to truſt in riches.</hi> The reaſon: <hi>For they are vncertaine.</hi> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> affirmatiuely: <hi>But in the liuing God.</hi> The reaſons are two. Firſt, he is the <hi>liuing God.</hi> Next, <hi>He giues vs richly all things to enioy.</hi> Where foure degrees of Gods boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and mercie are mentioned. Firſt, he giues generally: <hi>All things.</hi> Next abundantly: <hi>All things richly.</hi> Then freely: <hi>He giues all things.</hi> Laſtly effectually: <hi>To enioy.</hi> It is vnpoſſible the things of this world ſhould come to our hands with better conditions.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Firſt, charge them <hi>That they be not high minded.</hi> It is the nature of greatneſſe, when it comes, to blow vp the heart, as a bladder is blowne with a quill. And our Apoſtle ſaid in the ninth verſe: <hi>The rich fal into luſts
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20569:28"/>and temptations. Societ as quaedameſt, etiam nominis, vitijs &amp; diuitijs,</hi> ſaith Sidonius: <hi>Wealth and wickedneſſe begin both with a letter, and are ſeldome aſunder.</hi> And as he that drinks wine ſhall feele it fume into his head, though he be neuer ſo ſober; ſo riches and all worldly greatnes are a cup of fuming wine, which the beſt man that liues ſhal feele ſuming in his heart, and ſome are made ſtarke drunken withall. <hi>Eſ.</hi> 29.9. <hi>They are drunke, but not with wine.</hi> And as wormes breed in the heart of trees, and they tell of toades and ſerpents that haue bene found in the midſt of a great ſtone; ſo <hi>pride the worme of wealth,</hi> (ſo Saint Auſtine calles it) commonly breedeth in the ſpirit of rich men. And this is the reaſon why the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the firſt place giues warning of it. This high mindedueſſe, if I may ſtand a little to expound it, thus workes in thoſe that haue it. Firſt, he values and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemes himſelfe about that he is. His vnderſtanding being corrupted and blinded, he apprehends great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in himſelfe, that he is rich, that he is great, that he is wiſe, that he is able: whereupon he affects himſelfe in his will, and delights in his owne imagination. <hi>Ier.</hi> 22.23. <hi>I dwel in Libanon, &amp; make my neſt in the high Cedars.</hi> This thought makes the action of pride complete; and it is not neceſſarie that a man in good earneſt and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally thinke thus, but it is the complete action of a high mind to haue the paſſions of it. The errours of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are two. Firſt, that he forgets God to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that he hath. Next, that he ſees not the imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and miſerie, and wants attending that he hath. But is like a countrey man, that comes into a ſhop, and hauing no skill, buyes at a deare rate, and holds in great account, mingled and counterfet wares, becauſe he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20569:28"/>hath no skill: ſo his owne heart beguileth him. This is the firſt working of a high mind. Then ſecondly, vpon this apprehenſion he preferres himſelfe afore others, as good, or better then himſelfe: yea he deſpiſeth others. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11. <hi>God, I thanke thee, I am not as other men; or as this Publican.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.10. <hi>Who is Dauid, and what is the ſonne of Iſhai?</hi> Thirdly, he thinkes himſelfe worthie of any thing he deſires, and thereupon inordinately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trudes himſelfe into all greatneſſe and promotion, as if of right it were due to him. Like <hi>the Spider</hi> that being but a poyſon-full vermine, yet <hi>climes to the rooffe of the Kings pallace. Pro.</hi> 30.28: And <hi>the thiſtle</hi> that Iehoaſh the King of Iſrael telles of. 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.9. that <hi>ſent to the Cedar of Libanon to giue him his daughter to be his ſonnes wife.</hi> Fourthly, he makes his owne corrupt will and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the rule of his actions, thinking ſo well of his owne doings, that he growes inſolent and incorrigible, and will abide no teaching; like Caine, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.9. <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi> He thought God did him wrong to queſtion with him about his brother; his brother was old enough to looke to himſelfe. Fiftly, he ſhewes his ſpirit in outward behauiour, in words, in geſture, in apparell, in building, in furniture, in exceſſe of meate and drinke. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The daughters of Sion are hauty, &amp; walke with their neckes stretched out, and wandring eyes, minſing as they go: Their head tires, and rings, and muf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers.</hi> Finally, in his heart, he refuſeth all obedience to God, thinking it a baſe thing to be ſubiect to his word, or ordinances. <hi>Iob</hi> 21.15. <hi>Who is the Almightie, that we ſhould ſerue him? and what ſhould we get by praying to him?</hi> Theſe are the characters of a high minde, whoſe ſecret thoughts are noted by the holy Ghoſt; that we
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20569:29"/>may ſee the peſtilencie of that which the Apoſtle, here, giues warning of. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 18.7. <hi>I ſit a Queene. Dan.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Is not this great Babel, that I haue built by the might of my power? Obad. ver.</hi> 4. <hi>Thou exalteſt thy ſelfe as an Eagle, and makeſt thy neſt among the ſtarres.</hi> But it is a better way to heare what God ſaies, <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Let not the wiſe man glorie in his wiſedome, nor the ſtrong man glorie in his ſtrength, nor the rich man glorie in his riches: but let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he vnderstand and know me; ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 I haue now ſhewed what it is that rich men muſt auoide, but I muſt adde, that poore men, and meane perſons, muſt auoide it too. For it is a venime that poyſons the baſeſt alſo. Hagar Abrahams bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, was no ſuch goodly ſtuffe, and yet <hi>Gen.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Sarah her miſtris was deſpiſed in her eyes.</hi> And 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. we reade how the refuſe of the people <hi>deſpiſed</hi> the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. Thus it fares at this day among vs; ſeruants deſpiſe their maſters, the people reuerence not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, the graue Magiſtrates of this very Citie receiue not the pledges of reſpect. Iob ſaieth, when he was a Magiſtrate, and <hi>walked through the ſtreete, the young men ſaw him and hid themſelues, the aged roſe and ſtood vp: the eare that heard him bleſſed him, and the eye that ſaw him gaue witneſſe to him, Iob.</hi> 29.7. Now yong man, Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices, ſeruants, the common ſort, are ſo farre from hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelues, or riſing vp, that I haue often ſeene the Magiſtrate faced, and almoſt brow-beaten, as he hath gone by: but that due obſeruance and honour, that, by baring the head, bowing the knee, ſhewing awfull reſpect, they ſhould yeeld to ſo publike Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates in ſo honourable a Citie, I haue ſeldome ſeene.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20569:29"/>The reaſon is, that Preſumption and arrogancy fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes youth and baſeneſſe, as well as wealth. A paltrie cottage will ſend out as much ſmoke as a great houſe. A rotten log that is all ſap, will yeeld as much ſaw duſt, as ſound timber. The beſt motiue I can propound to all yong people and ſeruants, is this; ſo to carrie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues toward their maſters, as they would their owne ſeruants another day ſhould carrie themſelues toward them: and ſo to honour their Magiſtrate, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues would looke to be honoured, when by their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing, God ſhould heareafter aduance them to the like place.</p>
            <p n="11">11. In the ſecond place againe Negatiuely: <hi>Charge them not to trust in riches.</hi> The companion of pride is confidence in that which a man hath: the Prophet Hab. 1.16. ſayes, <hi>They ſacrifice to their net, and burne incenſe to their yarne:</hi> the meaning is, that the ſame confidence which by <hi>ſacrifice</hi> and <hi>incenſe</hi> we proteſt to God, they put in their wealth. And Iob 31.24. it is noted to be a paſſion in the couetous rich man, to <hi>make gold</hi> his <hi>hope,</hi> and to <hi>ſay to the wedge of gold; Thou art my confidence:</hi> where the Septuagint tranſlate, <hi>If I haue wedded my ſelfe to gold,</hi> becauſe they dote vpon it as a man doth on the beautie of his wife: and therfore he addes, <hi>If I beheld the Sunne when it ſhined, or the Moone walking in her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If my heart did flatter me in ſecret, or if my mouth haue kiſſed my hand.</hi> For theſe are the paſſions of the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, to delight in the beautie of riches, and ſecreetly, in their heart to kiſſe them, and flatter themſelues in their abundance, as if gold were their <hi>Sunne</hi> by day, and ſilure their <hi>Moone</hi> by night. So Pro. 10.15. <hi>The rich mans goods are his ſtrong city.</hi> And Eccleſi. 40.25. <hi>Gold &amp; ſiluer faſten
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20569:30"/>the feete:</hi> that is to ſay, The Couetous man thinkes he ſtands firme on no ground but paued with gold. As Luke. 12.19. <hi>I will ſay to my ſoule; Soule, thou haſt much wealth laied vp for many yeares: liue at eaſe, and take thy pleaſure.</hi> This is the confidence that rich men put in their riches.</p>
            <p n="12">12 But the Apoſtle giues a reaſon againſt this: They are <hi>vncertaine.</hi> Which is a good reaſon; for <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Truſt</hi> ſhould be planted vpon that which is firme and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, leſt it deceiue vs. The Greeke word here vſed, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, meanes that it is not <hi>apparently manifeſt,</hi> that our riches are that we take them for; we preſume of their goodnes, but we may be deceiued: as <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.22. they are called <hi>Deceiueable riches.</hi> This vncertaintie of riches and al worldly greatneſſe is threefold. Firſt, they are not ſure to abide with him that hath them in moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Wilt thou caſt thine eye vpon that which is nothing? for riches betakes her to her wings, and as an Eagle flies away into the heauens.</hi> And as a bird ſhut vp in a cage, will away ſuddenly whenſoeuer ſhe ſpies a hole open; ſo worldly wealth ſlides away through a hundred holes. <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.27. <hi>As a cage full of birds, ſo are their houſes full of riches:</hi> and 17.11. <hi>As the Partrich gathers her yong, ſo is he that gets riches vniustly.</hi> They write of the Partrich, that ſhe will ſteale the egges of other birds, and call their yong ones that ſhe neuer hatcht; but when they are flig and can flie, they all leaue her againe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and calling when they are gone, and ſhe that had many running after her for a time, by &amp; by hath none at all. So, ſaith the holy Ghoſt, it ſhall be with him that truſts in his riches. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.3. <hi>I ſaw him well rooted like a tree, and ſuddenly I curſed his habita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion:</hi> that is to ſay,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20569:30"/>I abhorred the vncertaintie of his ſtate, and in my mind preſaged the ruine of it. The experience of all times and perſons confirmes this. And the very Gentiles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed it more then many Chriſtians do. <hi>Zonaras, pag.</hi> 32. <hi>Tom.</hi> 2. writes, that the manner was among the Romanes, <hi>When any triumphed, that an Officer ſtood behinde him, and bad him,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Looke what was behinde him: and there he ſaw a whip and a bell, to admoniſh him,</hi> that, for all his preſent greatnes, yet in time he might fall into the laſhes of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that as a bell it ſhould ſound, and all his friends ſhould heare it. Thus fell Iob and Nebuchadnezzar: thus Beliſarius, that hauing ſometime bene the moſt honourable, wealthy, and powerfull in the Empire, in his old age begged from doore to doore, and being blind, was led by a boy begging in the ſtreets, <hi>Beliſario obolum date.</hi> Paulus Aemilius telles of a great man, that boaſting of his proſperity, as if nothing could ſhake it, was admoniſhed by his friend, <hi>Solam ir am Numinis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul abeſſe, à tam ſecundis rebus non poſſe: Gods anger could not long forbeare ſo great proſperity:</hi> and ſhortly after fell into that wofull miſery, that greater hath not bin heard of. The moſt renowmed <hi>Emperour Fredericke</hi> loſt all, and ſued to be made but the Sexton of a Church. How many great Merchants haue ſuddenly loſt all? how many Noblemen haue ſpent all? how many wealthy perſons haue come to extreme pouerty? All ſtories diuine and humane ſhew this to be true. Few Sondayes come ouer our head, but decayed houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or ſhipwrackt merchants, are gathered for. The wealth therefore of this world is compard to <hi>a tree</hi> that caſts his leaues, and is ſoone blowne downe. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 37.35.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:20569:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>neſſe vntruſtie.</hi> This kind of vncertaintie is properly in being occaſions of ſinne, as our Apoſtle teaches in the ninth verſe. They puffe vp the heart, they intice to ſecuritie, they are bauds to wantonnes; and when they leaue a man, they fill his heart with diſcontent and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring. <hi>Quantum, cum habentur, haeret amor, tantum cum ſubtrahuntur vrit dolor: We loue them not ſo well when we haue them, but we ſorrow as much after them when they are gone.</hi> He that hath moſt is neuer ſatisfied, if once he fall to loue them. A ſponge is holden to be a liuing creature, but it hath no parts. It is all belly to ſucke in and digeſt, nothing elſe: ſo is it with a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man, he is <hi>all belly,</hi> whatſoeuer he doth tends to getting. But of all other temptations that follow riches, none like the ſtrange alteration they make in the minde of man vpon their coming; that he which before was louing, and humble, and patient, and contented, and religious, and zealous, and chaſte, and ſober, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, now growes ſo altered into the contrary, that he is not himſelfe. They write of one of Euripides Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſo acted by the Players, that it made ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion in the beholders, that they all went home in a paſſion of phrenſie, pronouncing Iambicks, and grew into ſuch a veine of tragedy-playing, pacing and acting it in the ſtreetes as they went, with the louely words of Perſeus to his Andromeda, that it was long ere their diſtemper could be ſwaged againe. This Tragedy made the ſpectatours no madder, then, in our time we haue ſeene, worldly greatneſſe to do many men; who haue gone to the Theater ſober enough: but when wealth and riches, and worldly greatneſſe haue preſented the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, vpon the Stage, vnto them, and with their loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20569:31"/>aſpect a little inchanted them; there hath bene no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing with them but vanity and preſumption. We haue heard much of the efficacie of muſicke, what paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and alterations it will worke in the mind of man, and how it will put him into fits, beſide himſelfe: but I will tell you a ſtorie in Saxo Grammaticus. There was in the King of Denmarks Court one that played on a Harpe ſo exquiſitly, that it was ſaid he could put men into what paſſion he liſted, though it were into furie and madneſſe. One deſirous to make the triall, would heare him, but ſo that diuerſe gentlemen, ſtanding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loofe off out of the hearing, ſhould be ready to come in, and ſtay the muſick, if, they ſaw him in any diſtemper. Things thus ordered, the Muſitian began to play: and firſt he ſtrooke ſo deepe and ſweete a note, that he put the man into dumps, that he ſtood like one forlorne with care, his hat in his eyes, his armes wreathed, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lamenting. Then the Muſitian began a new note, and plaied nothing but mirth and deuices, that the man began to leaue his dumps, and fall a dancing. But in the third place he ſo varied his notes, and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees wrought vpon the man, according as he ſaw him incline, that from dancing he brought him to ſhowting vntill he grew franticke, and ſlue foure that came in to ſtay him. If riches be not vſed the wiſelier, they do the ſame that this Harper did. Firſt, in the beginning, when a man is gathering them together, they fill him with care and reſtleſneſſe, that nothing is more miſerable then a man carking after the world. Then, in the ſecond place, when he hath taſted their ſweetneſſe, and is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten through his trauel, when he comes to be a maiſter, he falles a dancing, and ſhewes the vanitie and ſurque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:20569:32"/>of his minde: he ſpeakes proudly, his behauiour vaine, his apparell exceſſiue. And in this fitte his wife alſo dances with him. But when this fit is ouer, the third paſſion is Phrenſy, killing and ſlaying: he becomes a griping vſurer, and cuts the throate of many a man; &amp; is ſo ſtrong and violent in whatſoeuer he takes in hand that no man with ſafety may come within him. <hi>Ita ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum habitus inflectit modorum varietas: Thus riches make euerie man dance after their pipe. Sic vitijs vt diuitijs incubantes,</hi> ſayes <hi>Sidonius: They foster their ſinnes as wel as their riches that loue</hi> their riches. This is the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of riches, and the reaſon yeelded by the Apoſtle why no man ſhould truſt in them.</p>
            <p n="15">15 The next part of the charge is Affirmatiuely: <hi>But to truſt in the liuing God, who giues richly and things to enioy.</hi> In which words there are two reaſons aſſigned why they ſhould truſt in God. Firſt, he is <hi>the liuing God:</hi> who liues himſelfe by his owne perfection, and giues life to all other things. The life of God is his eternall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, when, by the immanent operation of his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and wil, as by his owne forme, he moues him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, &amp; giues motion &amp; vertue to all inferiours cauſes; being himſelfe the center, and firſt beginning of all mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not determined by any thing out of himſelfe. This life of God is <hi>Anima mundi:</hi> the ſoule of the world. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.25. <hi>In him we liue, and moue, and haue our being.</hi> And our Apoſtle mentions it to giue rich men to vnderſtand that if they haue neuer ſo much, yet there is no life or vertue in it, but as it ſhall pleaſe God to infuſe: and if a man haue nothing, yet truſting in God he can giue him life and liuelyhood, when all outward means lie dead. This is it our Sauiour meanes, <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.15. <hi>Though a man
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20569:32"/>haue abundance, yet his life ſtands not in his wealth.</hi> How then? The Prophet Dauid ſayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.15. <hi>The eyes of all waite vpon thee: And thou giueſt them their meate in due ſeaſon: thou filleſt all things liuing</hi> (not with bread, but) <hi>with thy good pleaſure.</hi> Note here, touching the life of God, firſt, that all ſecond cauſes, as riches, meate, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, comfort, are vncertaine &amp; vaine, if God forſake them. Next, when a man hath all things at hand that he can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, yet God by infuſing of his life into them, giues vs the fruition. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Man liues not by bread onely, but by euery word that comes out of the mouth of God.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dauid ſayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.7. <hi>Some put their truſt in chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, &amp; horſes, but we wil remember the name of Iehouah our God.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, All the power in the world is nothing, if God with hold his life from it. And thus we ſee, many times, death, and miſery, and want, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be in the midſt of abundance; when life, and comfort, and peace, and ſtrength, are found in pouerty. Thus the poore mans child growes vp, and many a one ſtraitned and ſcanted with want, yet liues in much peace; when iſſue failes, &amp; poſterity miſproues among the rich, and their houſes, euer anon, are ouerthrowne. This is the the firſt reaſon why <hi>To truſt in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16 The next is, <hi>He giues vs, richly, all things to enioy.</hi> Where, as I noted in the beginning, foure conditions of the gift of God are affirmed. Firſt, that he giues vs <hi>all things,</hi> generally either that we haue, or that we ſhall need, or can deſire. In this great variety and plenty that we ſee, all things come from him: &amp; in this great neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity wherein we neede ſo many things, he denies no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. He giues the king his Royalty, the Nobleman his Honour, the Captaine his ſtrength, the rich man his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20569:33"/>wealth. He giues vs health, and pleaſure, and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in the time of danger; and as Nathan ſaid to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.8. <hi>If all this were too little, he would yet giue vs more.</hi> He giues <hi>all things.</hi> Next, he giues abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>richly,</hi> as becomes the greatneſſe of a King. Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes, and the greateſt that liue, are faine to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure their gifts, becauſe their ſtore is not infinite; but, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4. <hi>God is rich in mercy.</hi> We reade of a Duke of Millan, that marrying his daughter to a ſon of England, he made a dinner of thirtie courſes, and, at euery courſe, gaue ſo many gifts, to euery gueſt at the table, as there were diſhes in the courſe. This was rich &amp; royall enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement; but God giues more <hi>richly.</hi> Thirdly, he giues <hi>freely:</hi> he exchanges not with vs for any thing that he receiues at our hand againe, but he <hi>giues,</hi> that is to ſay, without any deſert in vs, he conferres freely: for <hi>He will haue mercie vpon whom he will haue mercie, and will ſhew compaſſion vpon whom he will ſhew compaſſion. Exo.</hi> 33.19. Therefore wicked and vnworthy men are rich, and great, and honourable; and the heathen that haue not knowne his Name, enioy great abundance. No man doth ſo; but he that giues moſt can yet ſcarce be ſaid to do it <hi>freely,</hi> becauſe though he receiue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againe in the ſame kinde, yet he hath thankes, and enioyes loue and pleaſure from him he gratifies; which God, in many doth not; and if any be thankfull and loue him, that alſo is his gift whereby he preuented and ſtirred him vp. <hi>Amor Dei facit nos amabiles: Gods loue infuſed into vs makes vs ſuch as he can loue.</hi> Fourthly, he giues effectually, <hi>to enioy,</hi> that no malice or enuie, of the diuell or man, can take away the benefite of his gift from vs. He giues it, and ſo giues it, that he vpholds it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20569:33"/>to vs againſt loſſe and decay; and then giues vs comfort in it, and ſtrength to it, to ſerue our turne. He giueth ſtrength to our bread, warmnes to our clothes, cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to our health, and ſecuritie to our plentie. But there are yet two things more intended in the words. Firſt, he giues vs all things to <hi>vſe</hi> and <hi>occupie,</hi> and do good with, to our <hi>ſelues</hi> and <hi>others:</hi> not to hourd and locke vp, &amp; liue beſide it in baſeneſſe and penurie; as if our houſe ſhould be like the den of a Wolfe, nothing but to cram and hide therein whatſoeuer we lay hold on: for Solomon ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Go eate thy bread and drinke thy wine with ioy:</hi> that is, as the Chaldee Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſt expounds, <hi>Taſte thy bread, thy ſelfe, chearefully, and helpe the poore.</hi> Iob ſaith, 31.18. He <hi>eate not his meate alone, but the poore grew vp with him, and the fleece of his ſheepe warmed him.</hi> This man was more then the Iailor of his wealth to carrie the keyes. Next, the meaning is, to enioy that we haue <hi>well,</hi> and vſe it <hi>lawfully;</hi> not to beſtow it as we liſt our ſelus, according to the corrupt luſts of our hearts, vpon the vanities and exceſſes of the world, but as becometh the ſtewards of Gods gifts. For the rich man, in the Goſpell, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.19. was no miſer of his goods, but ſpent freely; yet for ſo much as he did it vpon exceſſe in apparell, and meate, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, he went to hell for it.</p>
            <p n="17">17 I cannot leaue this point thus, but muſt needs ſpend a little more time about it; and therefore I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech this honorable Audience to giue me leaue to deale freely and really. When God beſtowed this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of wealth vpon the land, he neuer intended that it ſhould be ſo abuſed, in prodigalitie and exceſſe: Drinking, and dicing, and gaming, and apparell, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20569:34"/>the moſt part of many a mans eſtate; to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of whordome, <hi>and ſuites at law,</hi> and other actions of prodigalitie. Many hundreds ſell their land, which God gaue them to enioy, and deſtroy their eſtates to maintaine theſe things: this is it that makes our gallants trudge ſo faſt betweene the Broker and the Vſurer. The exceſſe of apparell is ſuch, both in men and women, from the Ladie to the milkmaide, that it ſhould ſeeme they imagine, God gaue them their riches for nothing but to decke themſelues. The walles of old Babylon might haue bene kept in repaire with as little coſt as our women are; and a Ladies head is ſometime as rich as her husbands rent day. There is as much, poſſible, to be ſaid of men. I haue little hope to controll it. When Luther began to preach againſt the Popes pardons, a friend of his came to him, and gaue him this counſell: <hi>As good hold your tongue; the cuſtome is ſo ſtrong you wil do no good; go into your ſtudie and pray, Domine miſerere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri; and get you no anger.</hi> The ſame you may ſay to me, for any hope of reformation that I ſee. And if ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſtraint were intended, I make a queſtion whether our Ladyes, and citizens wiues, and ſome Preachers wiues among them too, would forbeare to do as the Dames of Rome did, when a motion was made to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge them a little of their iewels and coaches: they flocked together, and ſuffered no man to go into the Senate houſe, till they had let him ſee their reſolution. Cato might ſay his minde, but the women would haue their will. But the will and reſolution of the beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect in this land, be they women or men, ſhall not beare them out againſt the Almightie: who in his word hath controlled this exceſſe, &amp; by the Paſtors of his Church
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20569:34"/>in all ages condemned it euen to hell, their painting, their nakedneſſe, their inconſtancy in all faſhions, their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: the inſtruments of diſſoluteneſſe: their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as Nazianzen ſpeaketh: <hi>The ſophiſtrie of their lockes, turning their head into a ſtage for men to looke at.</hi> But this is nothing. Feare they not him that hath made heauen and earth, and hath throwne into ſudden miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and knockt downe, before their eyes, as gallant as themſelues, in the top of their pride? Feare they not ſickeneſſe, diſgrace, a loathſome age? O why art thou proud ô duſt and vanitie? vile earth, ſtinch lapped vp in ſilke, magnified dongue, guilded rottenneſſe, golden damnation? Do you not conſider (I will yet once more vrge the point, if paraduenture any pietie, any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, any grace, any memorie of Gods loue be left a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs) do you not conſider what hauocke ye make of Gods good gifts, that ſhould be ſpent to better pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; relieuing the poore, keeping houſe, paying of debts, bringing vp your children? Do you neuer call to minde the pretiouſneſſe of the time ſpent about theſe things, when ſcarce one houre in twentie foure and twenties is beſtowed in humble prayer and true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your knees, in your cloſet, vnto God? ſee you not what a banner you diſplay of a vaine minde, that minds nothing but theſe trifles? how you confound all order and ſtates, by going beyond your calling? what occaſions of ſinne and vncleanneſſe you offer to your ſelues and others? how you deface Gods workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, your bodies, as if he made them vnperfect, and you would mend them? <hi>Non cogitat vanitatem vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi, qui vniuerſas vanitates cogit in cutem ſuam: Such as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20569:35"/>hang vpon their skinne the vanitie of all things, little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the vanitie of euery thing.</hi> And ſo I come to the ſecond principall part of my text.</p>
            <p n="18">18 Wherein the Apoſtle <hi>charges</hi> them touching the <hi>vſe</hi> of their riches, <hi>To do good, to be rich in good workes, readie to diſtribute, willing to communicate.</hi> He admouiſheth them of three points. Firſt, the ſubſtance: <hi>to do good.</hi> Secondly, the quantitie, <hi>to be rich in doing good.</hi> Thirdly, the qualitie, <hi>to be ready and willing to do this.</hi> Touching the firſt point, it is to be obſerued, that our Apoſtle doth not particularly expreſſe and name any thing, as almes, or lending, or contributing this or that way; which yet they are bound vnto in expreſſe termes elſewhere; but onely in generall he bids them not withhold their riches, but <hi>communicate</hi> &amp; <hi>diſtribute</hi> them, to <hi>all good</hi> purpoſes, and be <hi>good</hi> and <hi>godly</hi> as well as <hi>rich,</hi> yea <hi>abound</hi> in godlineſſe as much as they do in wealth and proſperitie. The ſubſtance is, <hi>do good, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute, communicate,</hi> euery way: the firſt word imports all good, whatſoeuer belongs to a Chriſtian life, pietie, holineſſe, iuſtice, integritie, religion, all godlineſſe. The other two, <hi>diſtribute,</hi> and <hi>communicate,</hi> that good which properly is expected from rich men, that none elſe can do. The proper good of fire is to warme, the good of water is to waſh &amp; cleanſe, the good of meate to feede, the good of Phyſicke to cure; and the proper and ſpeciall good of rich men is to helpe and relieue by <hi>communicating</hi> and <hi>diſtributing,</hi> where there is want, either among the poore, or in the Church, or in the Common wealth. The which goodneſſe our Apoſtle moſt wiſely oppoſes againſt the manifold euil that they may do. For a great man with his riches may do much
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20569:35"/>hurt: he may oppreſſe the State wherein he liues twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty waies; by ingroſſing, by inhanſing, by monopolies, by vſury: he may oppreſſe his enemie: peruert iuſtice: giue bad example: hinder religion: ſupport hereſie: beare out himſelfe in any wickedneſſe (for, <hi>A gift in the boſome proſpers which way ſoeuer it goes.</hi>) This is it that hath filled this Citie, and all the world with oppreſſion, and bloudſhed, and whordome, and Atheiſme, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtrie, and blaſphemie, that a great man may do what he liſt; becauſe his riches affoord him the meanes, and are a buſh at his backe. This is it that makes the name of riches ſo odious in the Scripture, and rich folke ſo ſuſpected in the world. And this is it that cauſes many a man to ſeeke after greatnes, and authoritie, and place, and promotion, that he might be able to execute the luſts of his heart; as many loue to be mending the fire, not becauſe they care for mending it, but becauſe they would warme their fingers. From all this the Apoſtle reuokes vs to the <hi>doing of good.</hi> This is the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p n="19">19 The quantitie is, <hi>rich</hi> in good: the qualitie, <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi> and <hi>willing.</hi> In which words he teacheth how to conditionate our diſtribution; there muſt be <hi>Plenty</hi> and <hi>chearefulneſſe.</hi> Firſt, they muſt be rich and plentifull, as God hath bene to them. He giues <hi>richly all things,</hi> and expects that we ſhould diſtribute <hi>richly</hi> againe. This is done, when firſt we caſt our eyes vpon all ſorts of good that is to be done: the poore, in extremitie muſt be holpen: orphans and aged muſt be prouided for: our poore friends that are behind hand: priſoners, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed houſholders: yong tradeſmen that want ſtocks: muſt be thought on. We muſt be ready to helpe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward any publike good, Churches, highwaies, bridges,</p>
            <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
               <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:20569:36"/>
            <p>feede the hungry, to cloathe the naked, to prouide for the miſerable? Many a poore child is caſt naked, by death and pouertie of friends, vpon the world; it weeps in want, and yet knowes not it owne miſerie: many a young man and woman in their want, are ready to fall into deſperate courſes: many an honeſt houſholder doth all he is able, and yet ouercharged cannot reſcue himſelfe from ſecret want, pinching debts, heauie ſighs. O happie hand that helpes here, and happie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance that ſupplies all this want: a poore child by this meanes becomes an honeſt man, and ſomtimes a great ornament to his countrey: and the diſtreſſed are enabled either to ouercome, or comfortably to beare their affliction. Make the picture of this Mercie in a table, and hang it in your houſes: let it be a virgine faire and louely: her garments greene and orient: a crowne of gold vpon her head, the teares of compaſſion bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at her eyes, pitie and ruth ſitting in her face. Let her paths be milke where ſhe ſets her foote: let plentie lie in her lap, and multitudes of people draw their breath from her. Let her giue ſight to the blind, and feete to the lame, and ſtrength and comfort to the miſerable. Let the earth giue her all his riches, and the heauens their influence. Let her make the Sunne to ſhine, the day to riſe, the clouds to raine, the earth to be fruitfull. At her right hand place the Angels of heauen prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, at her left hand all Gods mercies attending. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her feete the diuell and couetouſneſſe. Let pride follow her in bands; let oppreſſion, and enuie, and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loue, and vnlawfull gaines, flie from her preſence: and write vpon her breaſt, in golden letters, <hi>O bona Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, alumna coeli, corona ſoli, haeres vitae, medicina mortis,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20569:36"/>ô bona Charitas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21 Let me yet put you in minde of ſome things that poſſible might be mended. The common priſons of this Citie, they ſay, are the dens of much miſchiefe: ſome that haue long lien in them ſet vp a ſchoole of wickedneſſe, and teach the reſt impudencie. So that which is Gods ordinance for reformation, becomes a meanes to bring them to further naughtineſſe. It were a worke inferiour to no other, if they were continually and ordinarily viſited by godly Preachers appointed therunto, that ſhould preach vnto them, catechiſe them, and ſee their order, and make relation therof to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate. Beſides, ſuch priſons as haue Ieſuites and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Seminaries in them, are daily viſited by Recuſants, who bring their friends with them for conference. And ſo by that meanes they are ſeduced, and others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in papiſtrie: Popiſh bookes are ſcattered abroad, and more hurt is done in the priſon (notwithſtanding the care of the Magiſtrate) then abroad. They which are in authoritie can tell how to order them better then I; but it were much good to Religion if that generation were a little more reſtrained. <hi>The King of Meth,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in Ireland, vpon an occaſion not much vnlike this, <hi>asked one how certaine noiſome birds that came flying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the realme, and bred there, might be deſtroyed; who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered him, Nidos eorum vbique deſtruendos: The way to be rid of them, was to deſtroy their neſts.</hi> If you will ſhew any zeale in rooting out papiſtry, and deſire to rid the Citie of it, the neſts and cages where the Ieſuits and Maſſe prieſts and ſhut vp, and breede, muſt be looked vnto: both priuate houſes, and the common priſons, where theſe vncleane birds are better entertained, then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:20569:37"/>honeſter men, and truer ſubiects.</p>
            <p n="22">22 And whereas ſubſidies, and loanes of money, and other taxations when neede is, are part of thoſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherby the goods and wealth of the ſubiect is <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated</hi> to the State; let me ſay ſomething of that too. It is a thing that wee ſhould readily yeeld to. A good King is no burden to his State, if it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that whatſoeuer the ſtomacke receiues from the mouth, is for the benefit of the whole body. The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate <hi>is eyes to the blinde, feete to the lame, father to the poore,</hi> watchman to the common wealth, <hi>Iob.</hi> 29.15. whiles priuate men ſit in reſt, without care or feare of the enemie; which he cannot be, without theſe things. It is reported that the principall cauſe of the loſſe of the Greeke Empire, by the late conqueſt which the Turke made of the famous Conſtantinople, was the churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſubiect toward their Emperour: the ſiege was foreſene, and motions were made for contribution toward the repaire of the walles, and certaine militarie charges, but the ſubiect drew backe, and pleaded want, vntill it was too late, and the Citie loſt: what time the Turke entring, and finding ſo much wealth in priuate mens houſes, amazed, lift vp his hands to heauen, and asked what they meant that had ſo much wealth, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to be thus deſtroyed, onely for want of vſing it. When I remember the benefits that God gaue vs when he brought his Maieſty in, &amp; his rare conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in maintaining Religion, and expoſing himſelfe and his children to the furie of the diuell and his Agents, for our ſakes; and when I thinke vpon the libertie that the Goſpell and Iuſtice obtaine vnder him; and when I reade, now and then, in my bookes, of the vaſt and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20569:37"/>confuſion that many a people liues in, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of vs, I wiſh that in lieu hereof his gracious Highnes, as long as he liues might receiue all contentement from vs againe. For all wiſe men know that the welfare of kingdomes flowes from the goodnes of the King. And therefore his Maieſtie is worthy of all he hath, and more, and we may with comfort contribute to his charges that we do, and if it were more. And ſo I come to the laſt part.</p>
            <p n="23">23 Wherein he admoniſhes touching the end why rich men muſt do all this, and the ſtate whereto they ſhall riſe thereby: <hi>That they may lay vp in ſtore, for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, a good foundation againſt the time to come: that they may lay hold vpon eternall life.</hi> The meaning is, that this is the way to bring themſelues to eternall happineſſe: for God is righteous, and will reward vnto euerie man that he well doth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. <hi>If thou do well, ſhalt thou not be rewarded?</hi> He would haue no man thinke that God will recompence euill for weldoing, or forget mercie and compaſſion. <hi>Deus reddit bona pro bonis, quia bonus eſt: mala pro malis, quia iuſtus eſt; bona pro malis, quia bonus &amp; iuſtus est; tantùm non reddit mala pro bonis, quia iniuſtus non eſt:</hi> ſayes Auguſtine. <hi>God renders good things for good, for he is good; euil things for euill, for he is iuſt; good things for euill becauſe he is good, and iuſt: onely he rewards not euill for good, becauſe he is not vniuſt.</hi> And the way to recouer this reward is to be <hi>rich in the worke of the Lord</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. For <hi>by this meanes an entrance into the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting kingdome ſhalbe richly miniſtred vnto vs.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. In ſteed of theſe riches we ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded according to Gods riches. <hi>Aeterna aeternus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit, mortalia co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fert mortalis; diuina Deus, peritura caducus:</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:20569:38"/>ſayes Prudentius.</p>
            <p n="24">24 This promiſe auouches three things. Firſt, that there is <hi>a time to come,</hi> an <hi>eternall life.</hi> For many rich are ſo beſotted with the preſent time of this life, that they thinke there is no other, or if there be, yet they deſire it not, but abandon themſelues ouer to the preſent. Thus the rich man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. <hi>I will ſay to my ſoule, Thou haſt much goods layed vp for many yeares: liue at eaſe, take thy pleaſure:</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. Dauid mentioneth ſome whoſe <hi>Portion is in this life;</hi> that is, which looke no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but our Apoſtle propounds vnto them the time to come, wherof it ſtands euery man in hand to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: for <hi>as the tree falls ſo it lyes,</hi> ſayes Solomon, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 11. Secondly, he affirmes the foundation of eternitie to be laid here, that all ſuch as will enioy the life to come, lay hold vpon it in this life. There is no queſtion of this point. For Abraham tells the rich man, being in hell torments: <hi>Remember that thou, in thy life time, receiuedst thy pleaſures; and likewiſe Lazarus paine: therefore he is glorified, and thou tormented.</hi> And the Apoſtle requiring them to lay <hi>a good foundation,</hi> implyes that the ſtate of the next life followes the ſtate of this, as the vpper buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding followes the foundation. If we liue well, that is a good foundation, if wickedly and diſobediently, that is a bad foundation. For, <hi>Iob</hi> 4. <hi>They that plow iniquitie, and ſow wickedneſſe, ſhall reape the ſame.</hi> This life is the field wherein he muſt ſow that will reape: the vineyard wherein he muſt labour that will receiue wages: the race wherein he muſt runne that will be crowned: the mart time wherein he muſt occupie his talent that will be a gainer: the warfare wherein he muſt fight valiantly that will be rewarded. <hi>Iohn</hi> 9. <hi>The night ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proches
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20569:38"/>wherin no man can work.</hi> Thirdly he affirmes, that as there is a time &amp; a life to come, the foundation wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is to be layed in this life: ſo humilitie of minde, and mercie, and goodneſſe, and readineſſe in diſtributing, is the way to apprehend it, and come vnto it: and all rich men thereby haue readie and infallible way vnto ſaluation. So ſaith S. Iohn, 1. Epiſt. 3.14. <hi>By this we know, we are tranſlated from death to life, if we loue our brethren.</hi> And therefore our Sauiour, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. bids, <hi>Make you friends with your riches, that they</hi> (your friends by exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting your almes) <hi>may receiue</hi> (and make way for you to enter) <hi>into euerlaſting habitations.</hi> But, of all other, the 25 of Matthew ſhewes this moſt plainely: where our bleſſed Sauiour ſhall ſay at the day of iudgement, to the godly, <hi>Come ye bleſſed, &amp;c.</hi> And this is the reaſon why almes, and mercie, and all good workes, are ſo commended in the Scripture, and in the Fathers, and haue thoſe high titles giuen vnto them, becauſe they are the things which God hath appointed vs to walk in for the working out of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p n="25">25 For the better vnderſtanding of which point, and that you may ſee the venime which the Church of Rome hath put into the doctrine of Almes, and all Good works: you muſt note that for the bringing man to heauen and happineſſe, two things muſt be done: Firſt, Gods iuſtice muſt be ſatisfied, and the price be paied which man, through his ſinne, owes to God. For God hauing giuen the Law for man to keepe entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in thought, word, and deede; and man hauing bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this law, by his ſinne; the iuſtice of God is ſuch, that he cannot, now, be ſaued, till the price be paied for this ſinne: and a iuſt and full ſatisfaction be made
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20569:39"/>to God for the breach of this law: the which no man can do by almes, or prayers, or any good workes; but by faith in Chriſt, whoſe death and obedience alone iuſtifieth from the law. But then, ſecondly, when Chriſt our Sauiour hath reconciled vs to his Father, and eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs into a new ſtate, that our ſinnes are pardoned; and obtained for vs the gift of eternall life: yet ſtill we muſt performe the conditions, and walke the way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Goſpell. As if the King freely, without deſert of mine, at the mediation of another, giue me a place about him, and neuer ſo much right vnto it; yet I am bound, if I will enioy it, to come vnto him, and do the things that the place requireth: and if he giue me a tree growing in his forreſt, this his gift tyes me to be at coſt to cut it downe, and bring it home, if I will haue it: and when I haue done, I cannot brag that by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and ſeruice, I merited the place; or by my coſt in carrying the tree, made my ſelfe worthy of the tree; as the Ieſuites ſpeake of their workes: but onely my deed is the way that leades to the fruition of that which is freely giuen me. And there cannot be produced a place in all the Scripture, nor a ſentence in all the Fathers, which extend our works any further, or make them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede the latitude of a meere condition, or way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we walke to that, which, not themſelues, but the bloud of Chriſt, hath deſerued. The Prophet Dauid was a holy man, and mercifull to the poore, yet when he comes to the point of meriting, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 143. he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires God <hi>Not to enter into iudgement</hi> with him; for <hi>no fleſh is righteous in his ſight.</hi> And, that which might giue an end to this controuerſie for euer; <hi>Apoc.</hi> 4.10. we reade <hi>the foure and twenty Elders had crownes vpon their heads,</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:20569:39"/>but yet when they came into the preſence of God, to worſhip him, <hi>They cast them downe before his Throne, and cried, Thou alone art worthy.</hi> Againe, within the ſame latitude of our workes, the Apoſtle ſaith, that thereby <hi>We lay hold vpon eternall life;</hi> becauſe as they are the way, ſo they giue confidence and aſſurance to the conſcience, and lay, through hope, the ground of ſaluation in our minde. For as he that keepes the way, is ſure to come to the end; ſo he that perſeueres in the way of a good life, is ſure to come to eternall life, and hath confidence, not becauſe he thinkes his workes are worthy, or deſerue it, but becauſe he knowes they are the way. 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>If our heart condemne vs not, we haue confidence toward God.</hi> Saint Ierome writes of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lario, a holy man, that when he died, and felt a motion of feare, he checkt himſelfe, <hi>Egredere anima mea, egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere; quid times? Septuaginta prope annis ſerviſti Chriſto, &amp; iam times? March on my ſoule, and ſet forward willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: why feareſt thou? theſe ſeuentie yeares thou haſt ſerued God, and wilt thou be now afraid?</hi> For as in a clocke, the finger makes not the clocke to go, but the clocke it: and yet it ſhewes how the clocke goes within. So our works. And as, after a long ſickneſſe, when a man feeles his ſtomacke come, his ſtrength, and ſleepe to amend, and his ſits to abate; he beginneth to conceiue certaine hope of life: euen ſo our workes are the ſignes of our election; and the forerunners of ſaluation, whereby we lay hold on it by hope and faith, and walke toward it. This is the Apoſtles meaning.</p>
            <p n="26">26 Let vs come to ſome application of it, and ſo end. When the foundation of eternall happineſſe is to be laid in this world, by liuing godly; and ſuch as will
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20569:40"/>enioy heauen muſt lay hold vpon it in this life; they much forget themſelues, that, by liuing in ſinne and wickedneſſe, lay the foundation of their owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For Iob ſaith of euery wicked man, 20.11. that <hi>His bones ſhall be filled with his ſinne, and it ſhall couch downe with him in the duſt,</hi> and 1. Ioh. 3.8. <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue you with vaine words; he that doth wickedly is a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man, and of the diuell.</hi> Euery man thinkes to haue eternall life, and yet few lay any foundation for it. If euer it were a time to cry out of ſinne, this is it, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Preachers may ſay with the Angel in Zach. 1. <hi>We haue gone through the world, and behold all the world ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſtill, and is at rest.</hi> And it cannot be ſaid of vs, as it was of the Amorites, that <hi>Their wickedneſſe is not yet complete: Gen.</hi> 15. For we ſee ſinne to be of that eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that there is ſcarce left any roome for the mercie of God to helpe vs. There are foure things that ſhew ſinne to be complete, and nothing wanting but the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible iudgements of God to be daily looked for. Firſt, when the ſinnes are great, like the ſinnes of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, Atheiſme, whoredome, Sodomie, bloudſhed, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Theſe are crying ſinnes, and there are no greater. Secondly, when they are ſo generall that all ſorts are wrapt in them. In Sodome there were not <hi>Ten good men, Gen.</hi> 18. <hi>but round about, from the young to the old,</hi> they followed wickedneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. and <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.12. <hi>All fleſh had corrupted their way vpon the earth.</hi> Thirdly, when it is done openly without ſhame or feare. <hi>Eſay</hi> 3.9. <hi>Their countenance teſtifieth against them; they ſhew their ſinnes like Sodome, they hide them not;</hi> like Abſolon that <hi>Lay with his fathers concubines in the ſight of all Iſrael.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.22. Fourthly, when it refuſeth
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20569:40"/>all admonition and reformation, and no Preaching can beate it downe: like the old world, that an hundred yeares together, all the while the Arke was in making, deſpiſed the preaching of Noah: and like Babilon. <hi>Ier.</hi> 51.9. <hi>We would haue cured Babel, but ſhee could not be healed.</hi> The ſinners of England are of this ſize. Let it be written with a pen of iron, and the point of a <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond. Ier.</hi> 17.1. No ſinne ſo great but it is among vs; and that which is greater then the greateſt, the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſinnes are, many times, either leaſt puniſhed, or not at all. And the courſe of ſinne is ſo generall, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to be counted very preciſe that will not ſweare and ſwagger with the worſt. But if any man cleaue, a little more then ordinarie, to Religion, that ſcarce ſutes with the ciuilitie of our time. And our ſinnes are ſo open that I muſt ſay with Bernard, <hi>They are become the fable of the world:</hi> that if we ſhould not ſpeake of them, euery man might call vs the groſſeſt diſſemblers of the world. <hi>Would God the Noahs of our time had left vs any peece of a garment to couer them.</hi> Neither will they endure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, but are iuſtified, and affront the Pulpit, that the greateſt Biſhop in the kingdome ſhall be cenſured if he deale with them. Yea the torrent of theſe things is ſo ſtrong, that it ſeems manifeſtly to tend to the diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all humane ſocietie. Three things maintaine ſociety, Religion, Iuſtice, and Order. Religion is piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully violated by Atheiſme, blaſphemie, hereſie, horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble profanenes. The Stages now in this city, wo is me that I ſhould liue to ſee it, toſſe the Scripture phraſe as commonly, as they do their Tobacco in their bawdy houſes. Iuſtice is deſtroyed by oppreſſion, rapine, bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie, extortion, partialitie. That of the Prophet, <hi>Eſay</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:20569:41"/>59. is verified: <hi>Iudgement is turned backward, &amp; Iuſtice ſtands aloofe: for truth is fallen in the ſtreete, and equitie cannot go.</hi> O the pitie of God! If truth had fallen in the deſert, it had bene no maruell: but that it ſhall fall in the ſtreete, where ſo many go vp and downe, and none to helpe it vp; and be ſo wounded with the fall that it ſhould be lamed, no vprightneſſe, no plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, no truth among men; this is lamentable. Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and order is profaned by contention, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the Magiſtrate, by whoredome, inceſt, ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, pride, drunkennes. Theſe things are too manifeſt: &amp; all that are guiltie muſt make account, when they haue run their race, that there is a heauen &amp; a God, whom it wil be a woful thing to loſe for the baſe pleaſures of this world. And in this paſſage I value all men alike, of what cloth ſoeuer his coate be made: he that layes the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation with firework, muſt look, in the end, to be blown vp. The great Nobleman, that thinkes God hath made him greater then others, for no purpoſe but that he might be bolder to ſin, then others: the wealthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that turns towns into ſheepe walks; ſell Benefices for ready mony: contriue hoſpitality into the narrow room of a poore lodging taken vp in the Citie: that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the ſtrength of the land by vnreaſonable renting the tenants: the Iudge that takes bribes, that iudges for fauour, that vpon the bench makes lawes, and iuſtice, and religion, ſtoope to his luſt: the Lawyer that pleads againſt the right, leades Iurie into periurie: ſpends Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both after Sabboth among clients, openly defying God to his face thereby, and proteſting that he loues his fee better then Gods ordinance: the ſharking Officer that receiues bribes, &amp; ſpares neither the King nor the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, but ſucks from them both what he can; and the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20569:41"/>Clergie man too that failes, either in life or teaching: or labours not effectually to feede the flocke whereof the holy Ghoſt hath made him Ouerſeer: for all that are ſuch as theſe, and all whatſoeuer that lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſinne, muſt needs build vpon condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And albeit my words may worke no great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, yet afore any man can deny this to be true, he muſt turne Atheiſt, and be certaine that my Text, and all Scripture, is falſe; and that there is no God, nor heauen, nor hell torments. A hard point to ſettle in the minde; yet if it be not ſo, all that liue in this vngodly ſort ſhall periſh eternally. For God in the Scripture hath ſaid it, and all the holy men, from the beginning of the world to this day, haue beleeued it.</p>
            <p n="27">27. The ſeruants of Chriſt, who by their obedience glorifie his name, ſhall do otherwiſe: whom againe and againe I exhort to go forward in laying hold vpon this eternity: let no tediouſneſſe of time or labour wearie you; let not the ſnares of this preſent world intrap you, but looking on Ieſus Chriſt the author and captaine of our faith, runne with patience the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, that the ſence and loue of this preſent world rob you not of the hope of the world to come. Looke vpon thoſe, who, in all ages, haue taken this courſe: the Prophets and Patriarkes, Apoſtles, and Chriſtians in times paſt, and as wiſe and noble ſpirits as euer liued; whom this world could neuer deceiue, the pleaſures thereof could not ſurpriſe them, nor all the greatneſſe therein tranſport them; they onely attended vpon God and the good which he ſet before their eyes: they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled vnder their feete all that, whatſoeuer it were, that could not be vſed with godlineſſe. They liued iuſtly,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20569:42"/>ſoberly, charitably, chaſtly, vprightly among all men: they called vpon God, were zealous for his word, ſought not themſelues but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon good of Church and State, &amp; only inquired how they might glorifie his name that ſo mercifuly redeemed them with his blood. Me thinkes I ſee them mounting themſelues aboue the cloudes, and trampling vnder their feet, all the vanities of this world; and with their hands wafting vs toward them, and calling alowd vpon vs to follow them, and haſten away, that the loue of riches, and pleaſure, and caſe, &amp; ſecurity, intercept vs not. They are gone before vs, and being crowned liue in the ioyfull ſociety of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels and the bleſſed Trinitie, where the chiefe of their ioy is, that they are deliuered from this wretched world. O happy life that ſhall neuer ſee death, nor heare any more the temptations of this wicked world: that ſhall lay all theſe things at our feet, and ſhew vs him that hath conquered them: where all this riches, and power, and greatnes, and abundance, and pleaſure, and euerie worldly ioy, ſhall haue no vſe; but God himſelfe ſhall be all in all; and ſuch as haue renounced theſe things, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted them to the ſeruice of God, ſhall for gold haue immortalitie, and for the pleaſure of ſin reape ioy and eternitie with God for euer: and that happineſſe which the ſoule of man either moſt deſires, or is moſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of. The fruition of God ſhall be their meate and drinke: the glorie conferred vpon them ſhall be their apparell; their delight, the ſociety of men &amp; Angels; the ioy of their hart, the depth of eternity. And now ô Lord our God the mercifull Father of all that ſeeke thee, inſpire our hearts, put backe the world, the diuell, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20569:42"/>the fleſh from vs. Ioyne vs to thy ſelfe now in this life by grace, and then in that life by glorie for Chriſts ſake; to whom with the holy Ghoſt, in the vnitie of the Trinitie, three perſons, and one immortall God, be rendred all honour, and glorie, and thankeſgiuing now and for euermore. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
